<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A full answer to all the popular objections that have yet appear'd, for not taking the oath of allegiance to their present Majesties particularly offer'd to the consideration of all such of the divines of the Church of England (and others) as are yet unsatisfied : shewing, both from Scripture and the laws of the land, the reasonableness thereof, and the ruining consequences, both to the nation and themselves, if not complied with / by a divine of the Church of England, and author of a late treatise entituled, A resolution of certain queries, concerning submission to the present government.</title>
            <author>Long, Thomas, 1621-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 207 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49115</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2967</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19546</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12561287</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12561287</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63211</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49115)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63211)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 768:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A full answer to all the popular objections that have yet appear'd, for not taking the oath of allegiance to their present Majesties particularly offer'd to the consideration of all such of the divines of the Church of England (and others) as are yet unsatisfied : shewing, both from Scripture and the laws of the land, the reasonableness thereof, and the ruining consequences, both to the nation and themselves, if not complied with / by a divine of the Church of England, and author of a late treatise entituled, A resolution of certain queries, concerning submission to the present government.</title>
                  <author>Long, Thomas, 1621-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 83 [i.e. 85], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and are to be sold by R. Baldwin ..., /</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63211:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63211:1"/>
            <p>A FULL ANSWER To all the <hi>Popular Objections</hi> That have yet Appear'd, For not Taking the Oath of ALLEGIANCE TO THEIR PRESENT MAJESTIES, Particularly offer'd to the <hi>Conſideration of all ſuch of the</hi> DIVINES OF THE Church of ENGLAND (And Others) as are yet UNSATISFIED: SHEWING, Both from Scripture and the Laws of the Land, the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonableneſs thereof, and the Ruining Conſequences, both to the Nation and Themſelves, if not Complied with.</p>
            <p>By a Divine of the Church of <hi>ENGLAND;</hi> and Author of a late Treatiſe entituled, <hi>A Reſolution of certain Queries, concerning Submiſſion to the Preſent Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Licenſed, and Entred according to Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>R. Baldwin</hi> in the <hi>Old-Bailey.</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:63211:2"/>
            <p>A full ANSWER To all the <hi>Popular Objections</hi> That have yet Appear'd, For not Taking the Oath of Allegiance TO THEIR <hi>Preſent MAJESTIES,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:63211:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:63211:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:63211:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63211:4"/>
            <head>A REQUEST TO ALL Such as are yet Unreſolved IN THE <hi>Caſe of Allegiance.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THere are few Men ſo ancient or wiſe, who may not ſtill improve their Judgments, and be made ſenſible of their Errors, and without ſhame do that which St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> did, to his great repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, make their Retractations. The effects of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices and Prepoſſeſſions of the Mind are like thoſe of the Diſeaſe of the Body, called the <hi>Jaundice,</hi> which repreſents things black or yellow, according to its own diſtemper, only that of the Mind is far more incurable than that of the Body. It is with Men as with new Veſſels, whatever ſtrong Liquors are firſt infuſed to them, they ſtill retain a ſmack and ſavour of them. No Tyranny is with more difficulty caſt off, than the Prejudice and Prepoſſeſſions of ſuch Principles by which
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63211:5"/>
we have been in our firſt Education captivated and dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matized. No leſs than a Miracle could divert St. <hi>Paul</hi> from that furious temper wherein he had been educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as a <hi>Phariſee:</hi> To evidence the truth hereof, I ſhall only inſtance in ſome learned and pious Men, that have been educated in the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> who having been inſtructed from their youth, <hi>that they ought to believe as the Church believes; that their Church is guided by an Infallible Spirit; that the Pope is Chriſt's Vicar and Plenipotentiary,</hi> are prepared to receive and believe all the Dictates of that Church, though con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Scriptures, to Reaſon and Sence, with equal veneration as the written Word. Hence it is, that they ſwallow the Doctrines of the <hi>Popes Supremacy,</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe one Prince and ſet up another, as he ſhall ſee cauſe, of his <hi>Infallibility</hi> in coining new Articles of Faith, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding what Chriſt commanded, and commanding what Chriſt forbid; of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> and <hi>Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of Wafers and Images,</hi> and offering more Prayers to the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> than to God and their Saviour, and ſome of them eſteem her Milk of equal vertue with Chriſt's Blood; and it is unaccountable how deaf they are to all thoſe charming Arguments, which from Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Reaſon, and Sence, have been irrefragably urged againſt them. Now though the grandeur of that Church, and the intereſt of ſome Men therein, may thus capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate many, yet I cannot, nor can my Brethren impute this blind obedience and implicit belief of learned Men, and ſuch as are piouſly inclined, to any thing more than to the prejudices of their Education. And we cannot but think it their duty to ſearch the Scriptures, to conſult their own Reaſon, and the Arguments of ſuch ſober, learned and pious Men, as differ from them in ſuch Doctrines; Nor is it impoſſible but we who
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:63211:5"/>
have been educated in the Church and Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> may have our Judgments captivated by ſome falſe Opinions and Principles concerning the Power of our Kings, and the Allegiance of Subjects; for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying of which, it is neceſſary to reflect on thoſe times wherein we had our Education, which I ſuppoſe was with many others, as with my ſelf, about the Year 41, but with the moſt of my Brethren ſince that time, whereof I ſhall give this brief account:</p>
            <p>It is evident to all Men of ſober principles, that have had any true relation of the riſe and progreſs of thoſe unhappy Diviſions and Wars, that they were begun and continued by a factious and diſcontented Party, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the vain pretences of the great danger that threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned our <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberties;</hi> which War (abating ſome groundleſs Fears and Jealouſies, occaſioned by ſome unuſual Acts of that beſt of Kings (and the beſt are not free from all faults) to which the iniquity of thoſe times, that reduced him to great exigence, had neceſſitated him) had no other cauſe, but the ambition of ſome, the diſcontent of others; and the hopes of the Jeſuits on one ſide, and of other Sects on the other ſide, to raiſe themſelves by the ruine of the eſtabliſhed Church, to which that bleſſed Prince was ſo devoted, as well as to the welfare of his Subjects, both in reſpect to the Laws and Liberties, that he ſacrificed his Life for their preſervation, as by the event, through the great mercy of God, it proved to be; for though that bloody War wrought great confuſion and deſtruction both before and after the death of the Royal Martyr, yet the diſſention of his enemies, occaſioned the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of each others wicked deſigns and practices, which are ſtill in remembrance, and abundantly juſtifie that gracious King (as do alſo many gracious condeſcentions
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63211:6"/>
and overtures for peace) againſt all their aſſaults and uſurpations. Wherefore when after divers confuſed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volutions it pleaſed God, by a Miracle of Mercy, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal the Royal Family, and to eſtabliſh the King on his Throne, the Church in its Rights, and the People in their Liberties, it is no wonder if ſome tranſports of Loyalty and Joy did carry the People to ſome degree of exceſs; for the people had now before their eyes a lively Image of <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, in the meekneſs and mercifulneſs of <hi>Charles</hi> the Second. And whereas the Parliaments under <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, had abridged him of a neceſſary Revenue, that under <hi>Charles</hi> the Second granted him even above his deſires; and as event pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, more then was conſiſtent with the welfare of the Nation; neither was the Clergy backward in their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of Loyalty, who with <hi>Mephiboſeth,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.30. were content not only to part with ſome of their juſt Poſſeſſions to thoſe that had uſurped them, but ready to ſay, <hi>Yea, let them take all, for as much as my Lord the King is come again in peace to his own houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now it was, that the Parliament prudently conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering what Miſeries the Nation endured by the fall of the Crown, made it their chief work to re-adorn and fix that by inlarging the Revenue, making new Statutes to ſecure the King's perſon againſt traiterous Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and requiring the people to declare, <hi>that it was not lawful on any pretence whatſoever,</hi> &amp;c. And divers things and perſons did tempt the King to think himſelf an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Prince.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Finch,</hi> an ancient Lawyer, did attribute to the King all the Divine Perfections, <hi>(viz)</hi> 
               <q>1. That of Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty, All Lands being held of him, no Action ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt him. 2. Omnipotence, having power
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63211:6"/>
of Life and Death over all his Subjects, whom he might command to ſerve in his Wars. 3. Omniſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, by his Intelligence at home and abroad. 4. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, in that nothing could be taken from him, and being an inviolable Majeſty. 5. Infinity and Ubiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, being preſent in all his Courts, and in all places with all perſons. 6. Perpetuity, in that the King never dies. 7. Juſtice, in that the King can do no wrong. 8. Perfection, in that he is never in Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, hath no corruption of Bloud, but the Crown aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoils all Crimes. 9. And Truth, in that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be eſtoped, or preſumed to declare a Falſhood. 10. And laſtly, Clemency in diſpenſing with Laws, and pardoning Offenders. Nor are ſome Stateſmen much behind. <hi>Hobs de Cive,</hi> c. 12. ſ. 1, 2. ſays, That the Rules of Good and Evil, Juſt and Unjuſt, Honeſt and Diſhoneſt are the Civil Laws, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whatever the Legiſlator commands, that is to be accounted good, what he forbids, is to be accounted evil; and therefore it is a wicked Speech, that Kings are not to be obeyed unleſs they command juſt things: That before Empires were eſtabliſhed, there was no ſuch thing as Juſt or Unjuſt, whoſe natures are rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to a command, and that every action is in its own nature indifferent, and that it becomes Juſt or Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt is from the Law of the Emperour, wherefore thoſe that are Emperours make things Juſt which they command to be done, and thoſe things Unjuſt which they forbid; but private men that would aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to themſelves the cognizance of Good and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, do aſpire to be like Kings, which cannot conſiſt with the ſafety of Government.</q> Such blaſphemous and peſtilential Doctrines would confound Heaven and Hell, and turn Men into Devils, and Order into Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:63211:7"/>The Doctrines of ſuch as <hi>Sibthorp</hi> and <hi>Manwaring</hi> on theſe Principles, might deſerve to be conſured for ſaying too little rather than too much, and <hi>Nero, Diocleſian,</hi> and all other Tyrants be juſtified in all their Cruelties againſt innocent Chriſtians: This were not only to ſtamp a Divine Character on all Kings, but to grant them a Divine Nature, whoſe will is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Law. Now although theſe venomous Eructati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of an Atheiſtical Spirit have not poyſoned ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, yet ſome have been infected by them, and the Opinion of an Abſolute and Arbitrary Power in the King, which the late King challenged to himſelf, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with too many: and the many Addreſſes made to him in compliance therewith, and the Doctrine of <hi>Non-reſiſtance</hi> and <hi>Paſſive Obedience,</hi> made him pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume of effecting that Deſign, the effects whereof were ſeen and felt in this Nation, and had not God in his great Mercy created an unexpected Deliverance for us, our condition might by this time have been as deplorable as thoſe of our Neighbouring Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>And now, my Bretheren, I hope that as none of you can approve of the King of <hi>France</hi> his Violati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his ſolemn and repeated Edicts on the behalf of his Proteſtant Subjects, and of the barbarous Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty executed on his Loyal and Innocent Subjects, to make them Proſelites to his own Perſwaſion; ſo neither can you approve of thoſe Endeavours which tended to the ſame end, which are leſs juſtifiable in our Caſe, where the Proteſtant Religion is eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Law, than where Popery was ſo ſettled: Nor can I blame the <hi>Hollanders</hi> for ſhaking off that Iron Yoak which the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> would have ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited on their Necks.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:63211:7"/>It will therefore be no diſparagment to any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to purſue a <hi>melius Inquirendum</hi> on thoſe Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples which he hath aſſumed: I know my Bretheren will not account it ſo in any learned Papiſt, or other Diſſenter, nor think it a ſhame to any ſuch, if upon better information he ſhould alter his Judgment, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially when he ſhall find that many ſerious, learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and unintereſted men do upon very probable Reaſons differ from him. I have therefore choſen to deal moſtly on the Authorities of ſuch Men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing prevented by the Learned and Elegant Author of the <hi>Caſe of Allegiance,</hi> in the Rhetorical and Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal part. And having in ſome haſte drawn up my former Treatiſe, I deſire the Reader to add theſe to their proper places.</p>
            <p>And firſt to qualifie the extravagant Expreſſions of <hi>Finch,</hi> I oppoſe the Judgment of <hi>Forteſcue,</hi> who, <hi>fol.</hi> 25. ſays, <hi>Ad hanc poteſtatem a populo effluxam Rex habet quo non licet ei alia poteſtate populo ſuo domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nari principatu namque nedum Regali ſed &amp; politico populo ſuo dominatur.</hi> The King is to Govern his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by no other Power, then that which flows from his People, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> a Political, not a Regal Power. And <hi>p.</hi> 32. <hi>Ad tutelam legis ſubditorum Rex erectus est:</hi> The King is ſet up for the Safeguard of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects Laws.</p>
            <p>
               <q>To the Freaks of <hi>Hobs,</hi> the Conceſſions of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, in anſwer to the nineteen Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, may be a full Anſwer. There being three kinds of Government, Abſolute Monarchy, Ariſtocracy, and Democracy, and all having particular Conveniencies and Inconveniencies; The Experience and Wiſdom of your Anceſtors, hath ſo moulded this out of a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of thoſe, as to give this Kingdom the Conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63211:8"/>
of all three, without the Inconveniencies of any one, as long as the Ballance hangs even between the three Eſtates, and they run joyntly in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Channels. The ill of Abſolute Monarchy is Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, of Ariſtocracy Faction and Diviſion, of Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy Tumults, Violence, and Licentiouſneſs: The good of Monarchy is Uniting a Nation under one Head, the good of Ariſtocracy is the conjunction of Counſel, in the ableſt perſons for the Publick good, the good of Democracy is Liberty, and the Courage and Induſtry which Liberty begets. The Lords be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing truſted with Judicatory Power, are an excellent Screen and Bank between the Prince and the People, by juſt Judgment to preſerve the Law, therefore the Power legally placed in both Houſes, is more than ſufficient to prevent and reſtrain the Power of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, and the Power of puniſhing is already in your hands according to Law.</q> That Kings are bound by the Coronation-Oath, we have the Acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, <hi>c.</hi> 15. declaring thus in Parliament, <hi>We conſidering that by the Bond of our Oath we be tied to the Obſervance and Defence of ſuch Laws,</hi> &amp;c. King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt ſpeaks to the ſame purpoſe, as King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt did, <hi>If</hi> (ſays he) <hi>we take the People as one Body or Maſs, then as the Head is ordained for the Body, and not the Body for the Head, ſo must a Righteous King know himſelf to be ordained for his People, and not his People for him.</hi> For though a King and his People be <hi>Relata,</hi> yet can he be no King if he want People and Subjects.</p>
            <p>Having met with two Diſcourſes pertinent to the preſent Occaſion, in the Writings of <hi>Pufendorf</hi> a learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Civilian, I have thought fit to tranſlate them, the Books being rarely in the hands of my Brethren:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63211:8"/>
The one deſcribes the Nature of an Abſolute and a Limited Monarchy, the other ſhews what Obedience Subjects owe to ſuch Princes as preſume to Govern contrary to the Eſtabliſhed Laws.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="text">
                        <head>Pufendorf Politica Inculpata, <hi>Printed</hi> 1679, <hi>p.</hi> 107, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>What temperaments ought to be uſed in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealths, and of what force they are, will cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear, if the difference betwixt an Abſolute Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and that which is Limited by Laws, be right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtood, which will be more requiſite becauſe of the pernicious Abuſe of the word Abſolute, which not being rightly underſtood hath given an opportunity to wicked Princes to vex the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and to commit many Wickedneſſes, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eaſie for Flatterers thereby to blow up the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition and other Vices of Princes, <hi>(viz.)</hi> You are an Abſolute Prince, therefore you may do what you pleaſe, oppreſs your Citizens and Neighbours that you may be called a great Man, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which Inferences ſeeing the worſt of men think to be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally deduced from that word, therefore it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come deteſtable in free Cities; yea, ſome learned men are not aſhamed to ſay, that an Abſolute Prince may do all that <hi>Nero</hi> did, under the notion of an Abſolute Prince: Therefore as this is the chief Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of particular men, that they can diſpoſe of their own things and actions, yet within the bounds of Nature, and this Liberty agrees with all men that are not ſubject to another's Empire: So when more men unite into a Civil Society, it is neceſſary that this Liberty ſhould exiſt in them as in a common Subject, <hi>(viz.)</hi> a Liberty to determine of the means
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63211:9"/>
requiſite to their own preſervation by their own di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcretion, which Liberty as it hath a right annexed to preſcribe thoſe means to the Subjects, and to compel them to Obedience is called Empire, whence in every Government there is an Abſolute Empire, <hi>(viz.)</hi> in Habit though not in Exerciſe, for it is a contradiction to be ſubject to none, and not to have a right to diſpoſe of what is his own. Now that Abſolute Empire is not in it ſelf unjuſt or intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, may eaſily be known from the end of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Government, for we do not therefore conſtitute Governments that men may act accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their Wills, without regard to the Law of Nature, but that proviſion may be made for the ſecurity of each particular by the united ſtrength and wealth of all; therefore to Govern Abſolutely, is nothing elſe but a power to preſcribe to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects ſuch means for procuring the Publick welfare as ſhall ſeem to the Governour's diſcretion moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing thereunto, and as preſent occaſions may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire.</p>
                        <p>Becauſe the Judgment of one Man in diſcerning what is expedient for the Publick ſafety, may be eaſily deceived, and there is not in all men ſuch ſoundneſs of mind as to be able to reſtrain their wills within reaſon in ſo great a Power, therefore it ſeemed expedient to many People nor to commit ſuch an Abſolute Power to one Man's Judgment, ſubject to Errours and prone to Vices, but to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to him a certain form and manner of Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring the Government, on the obſervation of which Form they obliged themſelves to obey.</p>
                        <p>Nor is there any injury done to Princes by this Limitation of the Empire, becauſe they are advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63211:9"/>
to that Empire by the Peoples choice; for if it ſeemed grievous to hold a Government, and not to have power to Adminiſter it Arbitrarily, he might have refuſed it; nor is it conſiſtent with his Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, upon ſuch acceptance of the Government, to endeavour afterwards by Fraud or Force to ſubvert the preſcribed Form. That which ſome object is very frivolous, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That whereas Kings are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by God who hath commanded them to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern well, to which end a fulneſs of Power is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite; and therefore it muſt be preſumed, that God hath given them a certain meaſure of Power, which neither they ought to ſuffer, nor the People require to be reſtrained; even as a Husband cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent that his Wife ſhould uſurp a Power over him, or proſtitute herſelf.</p>
                        <q>
                           <l>Doctus ſpectare lacunar</l>
                           <l>Doctus &amp; ad calices vigilanti ſtertere naſo.</l>
                        </q>
                        <p>Now though it be granted, that Empires are from God, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> God hath ordained that Government ſhould be, ſo it is left to the Arbitriment of ſuch Nations to whom God hath not preſcribed a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Form, to appoint what Form of Government they approve of; As for Example, There is no Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Precept, that a free People being about to chooſe a King, ſhould chooſe a <hi>Sigiſmond</hi> rather than a <hi>Henry;</hi> nor is there any particular Form of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment by Divine Right, wherefore it is wholly in the will of the People whether they will erect an Abſolute or a Limited Empire, provided that the Limitations contain nothing impious or contrary to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63211:10"/>
the ends of Government. And that you may right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtand by what kind of promiſe a Government ceaſeth to be Abſolute, we muſt conſider that a King accepting a Government binds himſelf to Adminiſter it juſtly, either by a general or ſpecial Promiſe, which commonly is confirmed by Oath; a general Promiſe may be either tacite or expreſs, a tacite Promiſe muſt be underſtood in the very acceptance of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, though it be not expreſſed, yet moſt frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is expreſt, an Oath and ſolemn Rights being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, nor is it unuſual in ſuch Promiſes to deſcribe the Office of a King by enumerating the chief parts, <hi>(viz.)</hi> to defend the Good, to puniſh the Evil, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter Juſtice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now ſuch Promiſes no way di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh the Abſoluteneſs of Government, the King by them is obliged to Govern Juſtly, but in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, or what means he ſhall uſe, is left to his diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but a ſpecial Promiſe in which both the manner and the means are expreſt, is two-fold, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the one binds only the Conſcience of the King, the other ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth the Obedience of the Subjects conditional al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. An Example of the firſt ſort is this: If a King promiſe that he will not commit Offices to a certain ſort of people; that he will grant to none ſuch privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges as ſhall be burdenſome to others; that he will make no new Laws, impoſe no new Tributes, nor uſe forreign Souldiers; When as yet there is no Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil eſtabliſhed which the King is bound to conſult in caſes wherein the ſafety of the Nation (the Supreme Law) may force him to recede from his promiſe; here the Adminiſtration of the Government is reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to certain Laws, and when the King without neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity ſhall do againſt the Laws, he is guilty of breach of Faith, yet the People have no power to refuſe the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63211:10"/>
King's Commands, or vacate his Acts, for if the King ſay, that the ſafety of the people neceſſitates him to extraordinary Actions, (and it muſt be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed that he ſays true) the Subjects have nothing to reply, ſeeing they did not reſerve to themſelves the cognizance of ſuch extraordinary Caſes; from whence it is clear, that a people doth not ſufficiently provide for themſelves, in giving the King a limited Empire, unleſs there be a Council conſtituted, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whoſe conſent the Prince alone cannot determine ſuch caſes. But then the Empire is more ſtrictly li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited, if it be expreſly agreed between King and People, that he ſhall govern according to certain fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Laws; and in certain Caſes conſult with his People and Nobles; and if he ſhall do otherwiſe, that the people ſhall not be obliged to obey him, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving promiſed not an abſolute but a legal Obedience; yet by ſuch fundamental Reſtrictions the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is not maimed, for all ſuch Acts as can be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in an abſolute Empire may be performed in this; nor in ſuch a Government doth a King ceaſe to be Supreme, for it doth not follow, that becauſe he cannot do all things after his own will, therefore he is not Supreme; nor becauſe I am not bound to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey him in all things, therefore I am his Superior or Equal, for Supreme and Abſolute are not the ſame, the one excludes a Supreme or Equal, the other im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies a power of doing all things at his own plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="text">
                        <head>Pufendorf, de Jure Nat. <hi>p. 1002.</hi> Quid ſi Princeps inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centem Civem, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>What is to be done if a Prince endeavours in an hoſtile manner to deſtroy an innocent Subject, who
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63211:11"/>
cannot fly from him? <hi>Anſw.</hi> A man can hardly conceive how the ſame perſon can ſuſtain the Name of a Prince and an Enemy; or how he can expect to be accounted Holy, whoſe Zeal inſpires him to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice an innocent Subject to his own luſt. He would conclude,<note place="margin">The true Caſe of <hi>England.</hi>
                           </note> that if he whoſe Duty it is to protect another, do unjuſtly become his enemy, he doth thereby releaſe that other of his obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to him, ſo far at leaſt that he may without uſing force ſeek protection from another againſt his furious aſſaults. And ſuch defence is then more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable, when the number of thoſe whom ſuch a Prince ſeeks to deſtroy is very great. But ſeeing that an inſtance of ſuch a Prince as ſeeks to deſtroy his innocent Subjects only for his luſt is very rare, a greater difficulty doth ariſe, what is to be done when a Prince, under pretence of Law, becomes injurious to his Subjects, by impoſing unjuſt Commands, ſuch as the Subject thinks he cannot obey, without ſin, which he judgeth worſe than death? If the executing of a Command be ſuch as I cannot perform without ſin, and no reaſon can be offered either from any fault of mine, nor from the conſideration of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic welfare, why I ſhould be conſtrained to execute ſuch an act, it plainly appears, that the Prince makes it his buſineſs to deſtroy an innocent Subject for his own luſt, and bears an hoſtile intention againſt me, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he acting not as a Prince, but as an Enemy, I may well ſuppoſe, that he hath releaſed my obligation to him as a Subject. And afterward, <hi>p.</hi> 1004, 1005. ſpeaking ſtill of an abſolute Prince, he ſays, what if he impoſe grievous Taxes without ſummoning a Council that may judge of the neceſſity of the good of the Common Weal do require them? what if ſome
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63211:11"/>
eminent men be unjuſtly cut off on pretence of Plots againſt the Prince, and by orderly proceſs of Juſtice? what if he keep not his promiſes, or obſerve not the priviledges formerly granted? if ſuch an abſolute Prince pretend great Crimes, or the neceſſity of the Common Weal, he ſhall be thought to have acted rightly; for all priviledges have this exception, unleſs the ſafety or neceſſity of the Common Weal do for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid them. But there is a great difference between theſe two poſitions, 1. That the People hath power to reſiſt the Magiſtrates and reduce them to better order, if the Magiſtrate doth not govern according to their pleaſure; And 2. That the People or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons have a right in the caſe of extreme danger, as when the Prince becomes an Enemy, to defend their ſafety againſt him; thus when it is ſaid, that a people which hath yielded themſelves to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, hath not thereby loſt the right of vindicating their liberty or ſafety; this muſt be underſtood in no other ſence than that a people may defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt the extreme and unjuſt force of the Prince, which defence, if it ſucceed well, it redeems their liberty, becauſe when the Prince becomes an enemy, he himſelf ſeems to abſolve his Subjects from their obligation to him, ſo that the Subject is not bound to return again under his yoak, no not altho' the Prince ſhould change his mind. There is no na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural connexion between theſe two, <hi>(viz.)</hi> An ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute power to procure the welfare of any one, And an abſolute power to deſtroy him at his pleaſure, nor can it be ſhewn, how ſuch a power in the Prince for the peace and ſecurity of the Subject, can oblige them when the Prince acts contrary. Therefore they infer amiſs, who ſay, That becauſe the ſupreme Prince is
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63211:12"/>
accountable only to God, therefore it was the will of, the people, when they made themſelves Subjects, to deprive themſelves of all right againſt their Prince, as if he that defends his life, againſt a violent aſſaulter doth thereby call him to judgment, as if ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence were an act of Juriſdiction, or as if beſides the neceſſity of ſelf-preſervation ſome ſpecial Call were required in him who defends his life againſt an unjuſt force, any more than he that ſeeks to depel hunger or thirſt with Meat and Drink, for as <hi>Grotius</hi> ſays right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if they who firſt ſet up a ſupreme power over them, ſhould have been demanded, whether they would impoſe this burden on themſelves, that they would rather chuſe to die, than in any caſe repel with Arms the unjuſt violence of their Superiors; they would have anſwered, that they never ſo intended, for that were a greater miſchief than what they ſought to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void by their conſenting to live under Government, before which time they lay open to injuries, but ſo as they might reſiſt them, but by ſuch a conſent they ſhould have bound themſelves to endure all manner of injuries from him whom they themſelves had armed, without any reſiſtance. A hazardous fight is a leſs evil than a certain death, <hi>p.</hi> 1008. Now none but abſolute Princes enjoy ſuch an inviolable ſanctity, not ſuch as are any way obnoxious to the People, nor ſuch as depart from the Government and plainly relinquiſh the Kingdom, whatſoever is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful againſt a private perſon, is lawful againſt a Prince, when they practice grievous Injuries. As alſo when a King ſeeks to alienate his Kingdom, or change the manner of Governing, it is then evident, that he doth not only do a vain act, but that if he perſiſt to effect his deſigns by force, the Subjects may
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63211:12"/>
oppoſe him by force. And, <hi>p.</hi> 40. of his <hi>Politica in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culpata,</hi> he reſolves this Caſe; That a perſon taken in War may promiſe to do for his liberty what his enemy hath power to force him to do, <hi>viz.</hi> he may ſwear never to bear Arms againſt his conqueror; this may be done without injury to his Prince, becauſe if the conqueror ſhould deſtroy him he could never do his Prince ſervice; but if his Prince and Country ſhould be afterward invaded by the conqueror, that not only ſeeks to take away that life and liberty which he granted him, but the lives and liberties of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, it may be lawful to defend himſelf by Arms againſt his conqueror, notwithſtanding his Oath, which implied an offenſive taking of Arms only; for to what purpoſe were life and liberty granted for the preſent time, if it ſhould not be lawful to defend it when aſſaulted afterward.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>After all my weak endeavours, in a buſineſs out of my ſphere, I have reaſon to doubt, that I ſhall not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with ſuch perſons as have withſtood the declared judgment of that great Council, to whom the cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance of this Affair doth properly belong, whoſe ability and integrity they cannot reaſonably ſuſpect. Yet with what ſubmiſſion would I become a Petitioner to my Superiors, on behalf of ſuch of my Brethren, as are known to be zealous <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> of Conſciences truly tender, that fear an Oath, Men that have ſtrict Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Loyalty, of pious and peaceable Lives and Converſations, and whoſe number in the Nation is ſo few, that they cannot be ſuſpected of deſigning any diſturbance to the Government, may not ſome time and forbearance be indulged to ſuch? what if until a Convocation be called, that they may be better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fomed? If any ſort of Men deſerve their Princes favour,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63211:13"/>
theſe are they; and I pray God, it may not be granted to Men of worſe Principles.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Cynthius aurem vellit.</hi> I ſhall rather therefore expoſtulate farther with my Brethren; Why ſhould you not ſubmit your private Judgments to the publick Judgment of the Nation? What better Counſel could you chuſe, than what the Nation did chuſe; or what better Methods could they take to prevent Confuſion? They did not drive away the King by fighting againſt him, neither did they fight for him, that was their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared Enemy. They ſet the Crown on the neareſt in the Royal Line, ſuch as love our Nation and Religion: Suppoſe the King had been actually dead, and the Crown (as it ought) had immediately deſcended to the preſent Queen, who conſidering the great trouble of the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration thereof in ſuch difficult times, ſhould have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, that the Adminiſtration might be committed to the preſent King, who is every way qualified for it, could ſuch a Meet-help have been denied? What Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Ingratitude then are they, who when that Great Prince took his life in his hands, and parted with all to ſave our lives and all that we have, if we ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe him that honor which without his running ſo great a hazard for us, could we in Duty have denied it him? I cannot think that either the Soveraignty of the Prince, or the Allegiance of the Subjects do ſtamp ſuch an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delible Character on them as can by no means be erazed. I am not bound to take baſe Metal for currant Coin, tho' it have the Royal Stamp; and if when a Subject of <hi>England,</hi> by reaſon of Poverty or Oppreſſion goeth into <hi>France</hi> for his ſafety and ſubſiſtance, and be enfranchiſed there, his Allegiance to his former Prince doth ceaſe; What diſparity of reaſon is there, if a King of <hi>England,</hi> having by Male adminiſtration made his Government
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:63211:13"/>
uneaſie and impacticable, flies to <hi>France,</hi> and becomes uncapable of governing and protecting his People, to affirm, that his Soveraignty and his Subjects Allegiance do ceaſe together? Once more, we cannot but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that ſuch an exchange of Princes as the hand of God, and the People have made, is a Bleſſing and no Robbery; why then ſhould we halt any longer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two Opinions, whom we ought to follow? If our preſent Soveraigns give us Protection, it will be juſtly expected, that we pay them our Allegiance. If any think that the late King hath ſtill a right, why do they not declare for him? a Neutrality in this Caſe is intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; for tho' ſome few may think themſelves obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in Conſcience by their former Oaths, yet many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, out of fear, or hopes of intereſt, or perhaps out of a ſecret affection to <hi>Popery,</hi> may refuſe to pay their O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the preſent Government; and our Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, not being able to diſcern and judge of the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of Men, will take all ſuch Recuſants for Enemies, and that they that are not with them are againſt them, and only wait for an opportunity to do them miſchief; and the People will be apt to condemn them for <hi>Papiſts</hi> in Maſquerade: For as the Hiſtorian ſays, <hi>Non caret ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulo ſocietatis occultae qui manifeſto facinori obviari defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit:</hi> He gives a juſt ſuſpicion of a ſecret Confederacy, that neglects to obviate an apparent Danger. And then though deliverance ſhould come, ſuch men cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to partake of it; for the Controverſie now to be decided, is like that which <hi>Cicero</hi> obſerveth between the <hi>Romans</hi> and <hi>Carthaginians, Non an uter imperaret ſed an uter eſſet:</hi> Not which of the Kings ſhall Reign, but which ſhall be Ruined. And it would be a very ill requital, to expoſe him again to ruine, who once expoſed himſelf to ruine, that he might ſave us. But
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:63211:14"/>
I would ask the men of intereſt, <hi>Cui bono?</hi> what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit they think to reap, by hovering thus in the Air? if you are <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> can you think, that the late King will preſerve you in your Religion, Laws, and Liberties? if you are <hi>Papiſts,</hi> can you ſo depend on his crazy Life, as to think, that a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Prince would not ſucceed? and then by how much the more trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom and triumphant you have been for a ſhort time, by ſo much the more will you be fettered by ſevere and juſt Laws, that you may be ſo no more. In a word, they that in this juncture of Affairs will declare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves friends to neither party, do deſerve to be declared enemies to both. And as <hi>Livy</hi> ſays of <hi>Metius Suffetius,</hi> who doubting of the event of the War between the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> and <hi>Albans,</hi> hovered at a diſtance with his Army until the <hi>Romans</hi> had gotten the victory. That they condemned him to be torn in pieces with wild Horſes. The like is obſerved of <hi>Pub. Servilius, Medium ſe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendo nec plebis vetuit odium nec apud patres gratiam iniit,</hi> by behaving himſelf as a Neuter in the Civil Wars of <hi>Rome,</hi> thinking to retain the favour of the Senate and People, he incurred the diſpleaſure of both; whereas <hi>Appius,</hi> tho' he had taken the contrary party, upon a miſtake, <hi>patribus mire fuit gratus,</hi> was graciouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled and accepted of the Senate. Therefore I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with <hi>Suetonius, Quando alterum habiturus es ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micum aut ſocium jacienda est alea alterutri adherendum.</hi> Seeing you muſt have one to be your Friend or your Enemy, come to a reſolution, and adhere to him whom you chuſe to make your Friend.</p>
            <p>If after all that has been ſaid, be not ſatisfactory, as to the Caſe of Allegiance to their preſent Majeſties, and the Voting the Crown vacant, pray ſee the ſenſe of the Lords and Commons in the following Declaration, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="text">
                        <pb n="21" facs="tcp:63211:14"/>
                        <head>The Declaration of the Lords and Commons aſſembled at <hi>Weſtminiſter,</hi> preſented to their Highneſſes the Prince and Princeſs of <hi>Orange,</hi> at <hi>White-hall</hi> the <hi>13th</hi> of <hi>February, 1688/9.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>WHereas the late King <hi>James</hi> the Second, by the Aſſiſtance of divers Evil Counſellors, Judges, and Miniſters imployed by him, did endeavour to Subvert and Extirpate the Proteſtant Religion, and the Laws and Liberties of this Kingdom,</p>
                        <p>By Aſſuming and Exerciſing a Power of Diſpenſing with, and Suſpending Laws, and the Execution of Laws without Conſent of Parliament.</p>
                        <p>By Committing and Proſecuting divers worthy Prelates for humbly Petitioning to be excuſed from Concurring to the ſaid Aſſumed Power.</p>
                        <p>By iſſuing and cauſing to be executed a Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on under the Great Seal for Erecting a Court called the Court of Commiſſioners for Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes.</p>
                        <p>By Levying Money for and to the uſe of the Crown, by pretence of Prerogative, for other time and in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner than the ſame was Granted by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                        <p>By Raiſing and Keeping a Standing Army within this Kingdom in the time of Peace, without Conſent of Parliament, and Quartering Souldiers contrary to Law.</p>
                        <p>By cauſing ſeveral good Subjects being Proteſtants, to be Diſarmed, at the ſame time when Papiſts were both Armed and Imployed contrary to Law.</p>
                        <p>By Violating the Freedom of Election of Members to ſerve in Parliament.</p>
                        <p>By Proſecutions in the Court of King's Bench for Matters and Cauſes cognizable only in Parliament; and by divers other Arbitrary and Illegal Courſes.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="22" facs="tcp:63211:15"/>And whereas of late Years partial, corrupt, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualified Perſons have been returned and ſerved on Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in Tryals, and particularly divers Jurors in Tryals of High Treaſon which were not Free-holders.</p>
                        <p>And exceſſive Bail hath been required of Perſons committed in Criminal Caſes, to elude the benefit of the Laws made for the Liberty of the Subject.</p>
                        <p>And exceſſive Fines have been impoſed, and illegal and cruel Puniſhments inflicted.</p>
                        <p>And ſeveral Grants and Promiſes made of Fines and Forfeitures before any Conviction or Judgment againſt the perſons upon whom the ſame was to be levied.</p>
                        <p>All which are utterly and directly contrary to the known Laws and Statutes and Freedom of this Realm. And whereas the ſaid late King <hi>James</hi> the Second ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Abdicated the Government, and the Throne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby Vacant,</p>
                        <p>His Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> (whom it hath pleaſed Almighty God to make the Glorious Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Delivering this Kingdom from Popery and Arbitrary Power) did, by the Advice of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and divers principal Perſons of the Commons, cauſe Letters to be written to the Lords Spiritul and Temporal, being Proteſtants, and other Letters to the ſeveral Counties, Cities, Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, Boroughs and Cinque ports, for the chooſing of ſuch Perſons to repreſent them, as were of right to be ſent to Parliament, to Meet and Sit at <hi>Weſtminiſter</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the 22d day of <hi>January,</hi> in this Year 1688, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to ſuch an Eſtabliſhment, as that their Religion, Laws and Liberties might not again be in danger of being Subverted.</p>
                        <p>Upon which Letters, Elections have been accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly made.</p>
                        <p>And thereupon the ſaid Lords Spiritual and Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:63211:15"/>
and the Commons purſuant to their reſpective Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Elections, being now Aſſembled in a Full and Free Repreſentative of this Nation, taking into their moſt ſerious Conſiderations the beſt Means for attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ends aforeſaid,</p>
                        <p>Do in the firſt place, as their Anceſtors in like Caſes have uſually done, for the Vindicating and Aſſerting of their Ancient Rights and Liberties, Declare.</p>
                        <p>That the pretended Power of Suſpending of Laws or the Execution of Laws by Regal Authority, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Conſent of Parliament, is Illegal.</p>
                        <p>That the pretended Power of Diſpenſing with Laws or the Execution of Laws by Regal Authority, as it has been aſſumed and exerciſed of late, is Illegal.</p>
                        <p>That the Commiſſion for Erecting the late Court of Commiſſioners for Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes, and all other Commiſſions and Courts of like nature are Illegal and Pernicious.</p>
                        <p>That Levying of Money for, or to the uſe of the Crown, by pretence of Prerogative, without Grant of Parliament, or for longer time, or in other manner than the ſame is, or ſhall be Granted, is Illegal.</p>
                        <p>That it is the Right of the Subject to Petition the King; and all Commitments and Proſecutions for ſuch Petitioning, are Illegal.</p>
                        <p>That the Raiſing or Keeping a Standing Army with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Kingdom in time of Peace, unleſs it be with Conſent of Parliament, is againſt Law.</p>
                        <p>That the Subjects which are Proteſtants may have Arms for their Defence ſuitable to their Condition, and as allowed by Law.</p>
                        <p>That Election of Members of Parliament ought to be free.</p>
                        <p>That the Freedom of Speech and Debates or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in Parliament, ought not to be Impeached or
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:63211:16"/>
Queſtioned in any Court or place out of Parliament,</p>
                        <p>That exceſſive Bail ought not to be required, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive Fines impoſed, nor cruel and unuſual Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments inflicted.</p>
                        <p>That Jurors ought to be duly Impannelled and Returned, and Jurors which paſs upon Men in Tryals for High Treaſon, ought to be Free-holders.</p>
                        <p>That all Grants and Promiſes of Fines and Forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of particular perſons before Convicton, are Ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal and Void.</p>
                        <p>And that for Redreſs of all Grievances, and for the amending, ſtrengthening and preſerving of the Laws, Parliaments ought to be held frequently.</p>
                        <p>And they do Claim, Demand, and Inſiſt upon all and ſingular the Premiſes as their undoubted Right and Liberty: And that no Declarations, Judgments, Doings or Proceedings to the prejudice of the People in any of the ſaid Premiſes ought in any wiſe to be drawn hereafter into Conſequence or Example.</p>
                        <p>To which Demand of their Rights, they are parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly incouraged by the Declaration of his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> as being the only means for ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining a full Redreſs and Remedy therein.</p>
                        <p>Having therefore an intire Confidence that his ſaid Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> will perfect the Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance ſo far advanced by him, and will ſtill preſerve them from the Violation of their Rights, which they have here Aſſerted, and from all other Attempts upon their Religion, Laws and Liberties.</p>
                        <p>The ſaid Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons Aſſembled at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> Do Reſolve,</p>
                        <p>That <hi>William</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> Prince and Princeſs of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range,</hi> be, and be Declared King and Queen of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Dominions thereto belonging: To hold the Crown and Royal Dignity of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:63211:16"/>
the ſaid Kingdoms and Dominions, to them the ſaid Prince and Princeſs during their Lives, and the Life of the Survivor of them: And that the ſole and full Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of the Regal Power, be only in and exerciſed by him the ſaid Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> in the names of the ſaid Prince and Princeſs during their joynt Lives: And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their Deceaſes, the ſaid Crown and Royal Dignity of the ſaid Kingdoms and Dominions, to be to the Heirs of the Body of the ſaid Princeſs: And for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault of ſuch Iſſue, to the Princeſs <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>Denmark,</hi> and the Heirs of her Body: And for default of ſuch Iſſue, to the Heirs of the Body of the ſaid Prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>And they do pray the ſaid Prince and Princeſs of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range,</hi> do accept the ſame accordingly.</p>
                        <p>And that the Oaths hereafter mentioned, be taken by all Perſons of whom the Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy might be required by Law, inſtead of them, and that the ſaid Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy may be Abrogated.</p>
                        <q>
                           <p>
                              <hi>A. B.</hi> Do ſincerely Promiſe and Swear, that I will be Faithful, and bear true Allegiance to their Majeſties King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary. So help me GOD,</hi>&amp;c.</p>
                        </q>
                        <q>
                           <p>I <hi>A. B.</hi> Do Swear, That I do from my Heart Abhor, Detest and Abjure, as Impious and Heretical, this Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Doctrine and Poſition, That Princes Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or Deprived by the Pope or any Authority of the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> may be Depoſed or Murdered by the Subjects, or any other whatſoever. And I do Declare, That no Foreign Prince, Perſon, Prelate, State or Potentate, hath or ought to have any Juriſdiction, Power, Superiority, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence, or Authority Eccleſiaſtical or Spiritual within this Realm. <hi>So help me GOD,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                        </q>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:63211:17"/>Now if in the Judgment of the Great Counſel, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mature Deliberation, theſe evident Matters of Fact did amount to a juſt Cauſe to pronounce the Crown Void, I cannot perceive what in Juſtice they could do otherwiſe, then to lodge it where it is, the preſent Circumſtances in which the Nation was, requiring a ſpeedy Settlement: For which end it was provided after the Vacancy of the <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, the Electors were to agree in the Choice of another within thirty Days, or elſe to be allowed only Bread and Water until they had agreed. If it be objected, That the Crown ought to be ſet only on the Queen, it may be thus anſwered, That there is as little Deviation made as poſſibly could be; and that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent King might have claimed it by Conqueſt, with as much reaſon as either <hi>William</hi> called the Conqueror, or <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh; but he had alſo a better Title than either of thoſe, being nearer in Bloud then either of them; and the Title of his Lady being undoubtedly the next in Succeſſion, but by a ſuſpected Child was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to be excluded, ought to be (as happily it is) vindicated by her Royal Conſort, whereupon the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Government being by general Conſent conferred on him, during Life, it is no more than what he might have claimed, nor leſs than what they could have granted: And therefore there is no cauſe can be given why we ſhould not transfer our Allegiance to him, at leaſt in conjunction with the Queen; in the caſe of <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh the Nation did ſo before his marrying the Queen, in whom the right Title was, and much rather may we, when the Queen's Title is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, and the Teſt of all publick Acts and Writs are in both their Names; ſo that during the joynt Lives of the King and Queen, (ſuppoſing that King
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63211:17"/>
               <hi>James</hi> hath forfeited the Crown) our Allegiance is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly due as by the new Oath is required. But if yet any man ſhould ſcruple the taking this Oath, as not being ſatisfied that the right of Title is in the preſent King, I ſay that this is more than appears to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired either by the Letter of the Oath, or the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Authority that impoſed it.</p>
            <p>And, <hi>first,</hi> as to the intention of the Legiſlator, let it be conſidered, what other intent they could have in laying aſide the Oaths of Supremacy and Allegiance, wherein the right Title of the Prince in being was ſo punctually aſſerted, to make room for this wherein the aſſertory part is wholly omitted; but to prevent the objection of ſuch as ſhould pretend this too nice ſcruple of Conſcience, to which there being in the Nation ſo many Pretenders to a Liberty of Conſcience, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be forced, I do rationally believe, that the preſent Authority had a reſpect in penning the Oath ſo cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, for the Oath doth not ſay, (as without groſs Nonſence it can be ſuppoſed) <hi>I do promiſe that King</hi> William <hi>and Queen</hi> Mary <hi>are lawful King and Queen,</hi> &amp;c. but only <hi>that I will bear Faith and true Allegiance to King</hi> William <hi>and Queen</hi> Mary; which may be done, ſuppoſing that King <hi>William</hi> is only King <hi>de Facto,</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary de Jure;</hi> as in the Caſe of <hi>Henry</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth before mentioned. And as to the Letter of the Oath, though the Compariſon be odious, yet the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi> in the caſe of ſubſcribing the Engagement, may determine ſuch ſcrupulous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences; the words of the Engagement are, <hi>I do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to be True and Faithful to the Common-wealth of</hi> England, <hi>as it is now Eſtabliſhed without King or Lords:</hi> The words of the preſent Oath are, <hi>I do ſincerely Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe and Swear, that I will be Faithful, and bear true Allegiance to their Majeſties King</hi> William <hi>and Queen</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:63211:18"/>
Mary. Where firſt obſerve, that the Swearing doth no more add an Obligation to the Matter ſworn to in the Oath, than the Promiſe and Subſcription doth to the Matter of the Engagement.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Ingagement was for altering of the Species of the Government, from that which was moſt Noble, to that which was moſt Ignoble, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to an <hi>individuum vagum,</hi> there being then no Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The King then in being had in no caſe made a Deſertion or Forfeiture of his Crown, but endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured, with the hazard of his Life, to vindicate his juſt Title.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The Invader then was a Subject, and a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Uſurper, who by fraud and force had driven him from his right. All which conſiderations made a great difference between the legality of taking this Oath, and ſubſcribing that Ingagement.</p>
            <p>But here I muſt premiſe, that I do not inſiſt on this Inſtance, as if I thought the preſent King and Queen were only ſo <hi>de facto,</hi> for I am rationally and fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that they are rightfully King and Queen of <hi>England, &amp;c.</hi> as ever any of their Predeceſſors were.</p>
            <p>That learned Caſuiſt gives a higher and ſtricter or a lower and laxer ſence of the Engagement; the lower and laxer ſence he thus expreſſeth: <hi>Whereas for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, the Supreme Power, under which I am, is actually poſſeſſed by the Houſe of Commons, without King or Houſe of Lords, I promiſe, that, as long as I live under their protection, I will not contrive or attempt any act of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtility against them, but living quietly and peaceably, will endeavour faithfully in my Place and Calling to do what every good Member of a Common-wealth ought to do for the ſafety of my Country and preſervation of Civil Society therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:63211:18"/>And our Caſuits ſays, <hi>p.</hi> 106. <hi>There want not grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter probabilities of reaſon to induce us to believe, that this ſenſe is to be accounted the immediate and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red intent of the impoſers, who though they might have a more ſecret reſerved and ultimate intent, the ingager is not concerned in it,</hi> the Equivocation (if any) lieth on the Impoſers ſcore, not on the Subſcribers; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Many, both Divines and Lawyers, took it, which they would not have done in another ſenſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe if the Impoſers had intended to bind to more, they might have eaſily framed the words ſo as not to be capable of this lower conſtruction.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe it is uſual for new Governors to abſtain from harſh proceedings, even againſt thoſe whom they know to be diſaffected to their Government. <hi>Remiſſius imperanti melius paretur;</hi> therefore the Biſhops reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is, <hi>that when the Impoſer chuſeth words capable of a double ſenſe, it is neither neceſſary nor expedient, that the Promiſer do doubt which ſenſe the Impoſer doth mean, but may in prudence, and without violation to his conſcience, make his advantage of the ambiguity, and take it in the laxer ſenſe,</hi> becauſe ſince the Faith that is to be given, is intended to the behoof of him to whom it is given; it concerns him to take care, that his meaning be expreſſed in ſuch words, as may ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt his intent, which if he neglect, the promiſer is not bound to lay a greater obligation on himſelf than he needs to do; and though the impoſer might intend more under his ambiguous terms, yet the promiſer is not bound to take notice of it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Reader,</hi> if concerned, may ſee more in that Caſe, but I think this ſufficient and pertinent to the preſent Caſe.</p>
            <p>As to the Original of Supreme Power, and the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:63211:19"/>
reſulting from thence to the perſon of the King, I ſhall here ſubjoyn two excellent Diſcourſes of the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Civilian <hi>Pufendorf.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Original of Supreme Power.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THat Supreme Empire may have its effect, there is required, firſt, ſuch natural Strength as may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force the Subject to obey his Commands; and ſecondly, a Title or Authority by which he may enjoyn what is to be done or omitted; both theſe do flow from thoſe Contracts by which Societies are formed; for although no man can naturally transfund his ſtrength into another, yet that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may poſſeſs the ſtrength of others, to whoſe will they are obliged to apply their ſtrength, without reſiſtance or diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying his command: and when all do thus ſubmit their wills to the will of one, he then hath ſufficient power to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel them to Obedience. Thus</hi> Livy, <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 59. <hi>The Power of Empire conſiſts in the conſent of them that are to obey: and this Contract gives a clear Title by which the Empire is lawfully conſtituted, by a willing Submiſſion of the Subjects, and not by Violence: this is the immediate cauſe from whence Supreme Power, as a Moral Quality, doth reſult. And evident it is, that ſound Reaſon did dictate, (on the multiplication of Mankind) that their Honour, Peace, and Safety could not ſubſiſt without Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which neither could well be without a Supreme Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; Hence it is that the Higher Powers are ſaid to be appointed of God, as being the Author of the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; for not only thoſe things are ſaid to be of God which he doth inſtitute immediately without the intervention of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Humane Act, but thoſe alſo which men by the conduct of right reaſon, as the condition of times and places do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, have received in reference to that obligation which lies on them from God,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.2. <hi>That they may lead
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:63211:19"/>
a quiet and peaceable life,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Hence God in the Scripture approves of Empire as his Inſtitution, and by ſtrict Laws eſtabliſheth its San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity and Veneration. Thus</hi> Baecler <hi>on</hi> Grotius l. 1. c. 3. ſ. 6. <hi>The Supreme Power is not to be attributed only to the acts of Men, but the command of God, and the Law of Nature, or to ſuch acts of Men as are agreeable to the Law of Nature; for he that command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Society commanded the Order of Society, whereof Empire is the ſoul. The true ſence whereof is this, that the Divine Command doth exert it ſelf by the dictates of Reaſon, whereby Men underſtood that their peace and welfare, which is the end of the Law of Nature, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſubſiſt without Civil Society, nor that without a Supreme Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As to the fifth Commandment injoyning Obedience to Governours, that doth not exclude thoſe ſecond Cauſes by which their Power is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, as the Precept againſt theft excludes not the Original of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion. Governours are ſaid to be God's Vicegerents in this ſence, that becauſe the bare reſpect of the Law of Nature, and its Author, did not effect the Peace and Order of Mankind, that end is perfected by the efficacy of Civil Empire; for that a Society may obtain its end, God appointed by the Law of Nature the Order of Commanding and Obeying, in which, by God's will, and the dictates of Nature, there muſt be a Supremacy depending on none but God. But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this Supremacy ſhould be committed to one or more, and by what particular means the ſtate of the Government be conſtituted, this is meerly a Humane act. So</hi> Grotius <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>ſ.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That men agreed to live in Society not by any expreſs Command of God, but of their own accord, yet not without the will of God and the dictates of Reaſon; whence aroſe Civil Power, which St.</hi> Peter <hi>calls the Ordinance of Man,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.13.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Though this might ſuffice as to the riſe of Civil Authority, and the Veneration due to it, yet ſome aſcribe it to a higher Inſtitution, as</hi> Hornius de Civit. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>That it is ſo immediately from God, that no act of Man contributes to it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>So that where a free People do chooſe their King, they only deſign the perſon on whom there is a Majeſty immediately conferred by God; as in free Cities the Magiſtrate is elected by Suffrage of the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, but his power derived from the Supreme Governour. But this Aſſertion, though it have a fair reception among many, doth wholly deſtroy all the fundamental Laws that are agreed on between the Prince and People for the adminiſtration of Government; for by this there is a Majeſty aſcribed only to Kings, but denied to free Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:63211:20"/>
whereas there is the ſame Supremacy over the Subjects in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Commonwealth. Whereas therefore he makes God the only cauſe of Majeſty, who immediately on the Election of the People in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth that Majeſty into the King; wherein he conceives this Majeſty to be a Phyſical quality, as they do who hold, that Government is God's Ordinance ſo intirely, that no Creature doth contribute any thing to its Inſtitution, which bewrays a groſs ignorance of things Moral: As for his demand, How an extraordinary Splendor ſhould ſhine forth in him that is advanced to the Throne from an obſcure condition, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it came from God—, let it be conſidered by them who know not to diſcern ſhadows from ſubſtances. His Argument from God's ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Care over Princes, proves nothing, God having the ſame care of others; and many Kings have periſhed by Poyſons and Treaſons. His chief Argument is this:</hi> That ſeeing neither any individual Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, nor the Multitude have this Majeſty in themſelves, they cannot confer it on the King. <hi>Anſ. That a Moral quality, ſuch as Empire is, may be produced in another by the agreement of them who had it not formally in themſelves; As many Voices do make a Harmony, which no one could do. This Argument is like that of</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates, <hi>who would perſwade</hi> Alcibiades <hi>to adventure himſelf in the Aſſembly of the People, ſaying,</hi> If thou doſt contemn them ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, thou need'ſt not to fear them altogether. <hi>But ſeeing Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire doth conſist in the Subjects Conceſſions of Non-reſiſtance, and of their Strength and Wealth at the diſpoſe of the Emperour, theſe are the Seeds of Majeſty, which lying hid and diſperſed in ſingle perſons, do by a combination and agreement exert themſelves and produce a Majeſty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I cannot conceive how a wiſe Chriſtian King can delight to hear what ſome Flatterers may ſuggest; That God hath transferred on him that right of Government, which, by the Creation, was only in himſelf; and thence infer ſuch things as rob God of his Authority, to exalt the King, and would make men doubt, whether God had not abdicated all his Authority, and left it to Kings, and Kings conceive that they may do what they pleaſe impunely. But ſuppoſe a company of</hi> Banditti <hi>grow ſo numerous as to ſet up an Emperour of their own, and depoſe their lawful Prince, doth God transfer the Majeſty of this on that other? And the most of Kings owe their riſe to Conqueſts. And it is not impoſſible, but that the Father of a Family may have ſo numerous an Off-ſpring, that they may conſtitute their common Father to be their King; Doth this act transfer ſuch a Majeſty on him, or if be appoint a Succeſſour, or the ſeveral Families ſet up another than
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:63211:20"/>
ſuch a one as was appointed by him, perhaps a younger Brother, or a Servant, which is not against any Law of Nature, doth God beſtow ſuch a Majeſty on the Succeſſour? This is ſuch a Metempſychoſis of Majeſty as no wiſe man will deſire a farther diſproof of, ſeeing that whenſoever a Kingdom doth become void, it is left to the People to confer the Government, by their conſent and ſubmiſſion, to his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>So that this Author had no ſuch notion of a Divine Majeſty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiding in the perſon of a King as imprinted an indelible Character on him, which could not by any Vice or Miſcariage of his own be obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terated.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Such Polititians as write of the Majeſty of Governours, do diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh it into real and perſonal, and affirm the real Majeſty to be in the People, who had the power to conſtitute what form of Government they pleaſed, whether Monarchy or any other, and in caſe the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours in the Form conſtituted, do fail of Heirs or Succeſſours, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of the Government revolves on the Community: What is held on Condition may be forfeited, and on the Forfeiture returns to them that gave it. Thoſe Soveraigns that are limited by Law, and have not the whole Legiſlative Power, but are bound by Oaths to govern according to Law, may forfeit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tyranni in Exertitio do decidere Jure ſuo Hereditario:</hi> And if a King of <hi>England,</hi> who hath <hi>Regnum Pactionatum,</hi> makes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf an Abſolute Prince, he makes himſelf no King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> becauſe he alters the Species of Government.</p>
               <p>Puffendorph de Jure Naturae, &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 1008. <hi>But this Sanctity none but ſuch as are Abſolute Kings do enjoy, not ſuch as are under the Power of the People, nor ſuch as deſert the Government, or abdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the Kingdom, againſt (whom when they act things very injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous) whatever is lawful againſt a private perſon, is lawful against them. As alſo if a King that is conſtituted by his People, would a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienate his Kingdom, or alter the Form of Government, it is evident that he not only cannot do it, but if he continue to effect it by force, the People may reſiſt him by force.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Another difficult queſtion is, what is and what is not lawful in caſe of an unlawful Invaſion.</hi> (Here obſerve that the Invaſion by the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was not as to him unlawful, and therefore much more may be due to him than to unlawful Invadors.) <hi>What obligation may the commands of ſuch have, being in poſſeſſion of the Kingdom, becauſe force may compel a neceſſity of external O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, but not of ſuch an obligation of Conſcience, that if the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:63211:21"/>
obey not, he ſhall be guilty of Sin; in this Caſe, to avoid a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter evil, a man may be by force conſtrained to do what elſe he would abhor, which if we can by any means we ought to avoid. But what if the Invador having by force and evil arts got the poſſeſſion, yet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends he hath a right to it, and behaves himſelf as a good Prince, in this caſe it ſeems very probable, that he who is thus in poſſeſſion, ought to be accounted a lawful Prince, as long as there is no other that can challenge a better right; for this is agreeable to reaſon: Where the power of the Poſſeſſour doth prevail, and he behaves himſelf as a good Prince, every man ſhould rather regard the publick Welfare rather than expoſe it to perpetual Troubles and Revolutions for the ſake of an uncertain Governour; therefore when the People give conſent to ſuch an Invader, (at leaſt tacitly) they are really bound to yeild them Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; for thus, it is known, the firſt</hi> Caeſars <hi>obtained the Empire, yet St.</hi> Paul, Rom. 13. <hi>attributes a lawful Authority (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) to them, and that we ought to obey them for Conſcience ſake: And our Saviour commands us to give unto</hi> Caeſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Caeſar<hi>'s, when none elſe could claim a better right: And the Senate and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of</hi> Rome, <hi>had deſerted their ancient right for fear, and want of ſtrength, than as allowing that Dominion:</hi> To which purpoſe was that Statute of <hi>Henry</hi> the 7th, which provided, that none that obeyed the King <hi>(de facto)</hi> in being, ſhould be for that cauſe moleſted or troubled by any proceſs of Law, or Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And that of <hi>Nicetas Coniates</hi> is to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>That neither the Emperour that deſerts is to be ſought, nor he which is preſent to be expelled, even as in an Hereditary Kingdom where there are two or more Competitors, while the Conteſt depends, and is not determined by Treaty or Arms, it is moſt ſafe to obey him that is in poſſeſſion.</hi> To this alſo agrees that Defence of <hi>Caſſius,</hi> that ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with <hi>Niger</hi> againſt <hi>Severus,</hi> as <hi>Zephiline Epit. Dioniſ.</hi> and <hi>Zonarus Tom.</hi> 2. relate it, <hi>I neither knew you nor</hi> Niger, <hi>but being found in thoſe parts did not oppoſe you, but</hi> Julian; <hi>and ſeeing I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured the ſame thing as you did, I have not offended you, no, not in this, that I did not afterward come over to you; for neither would you have any of your Friends to go over to him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But what is to be done when any one uſurps the right of a lawful Prince that is expelled? What ſhall a good Subject do as long as the lawful Prince is in being to whom he ſeems to owe Obedience? In this caſe it is determinable, that matters may be reduced to ſuch a paſs that it may not only be lawful, but a duty to obey him that is by what means ſoever in poſſeſſion; for although his commands, for want
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:63211:21"/>
of a lawful Power, have not in themſelves the force of Obligation, yet the lawful Prince not being able to exerciſe his Office, it is the duty of a wiſe man ſo far to conſult his own affairs, as not to abandon the care of his life and fortunes, which, if he ſhould vainly reſiſt the Poſſeſſour, and provoke his wrath, he might do without any ſervice to his Country or the ejected Prince: And this ſome do infer from</hi> Rom. 13. <hi>where the Apoſtle injoyns Obedience not only for wrath,</hi> (i. e.) <hi>not contumaciouſly and unneſſarily to provoke the wrath of him that bears the Sword; and therefore for our own preſervation we ought to obey, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the Powers that are in poſſeſſion; for ſeeing the Commonwealth cannot ſubſiſt without Government, and the Poſſeſſour doth ſupply it, no good Subject ought to give occaſion of imbroyling the Nation by new troubles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But this is the greateſt ſcruple, How the Subject can at the ſame time be obliged to the Prince</hi> de Facto, <hi>and only in poſſeſſion, and to the Prince</hi> de Jure <hi>that is put out of poſſeſſion, when each ſeeketh the deſtruction of the other, for although the Subject ſhould ſwear Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to the Prince in poſſeſſion, that can no more make void his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to his rightful Prince, than the right of a Landlord can be made void by an agreement between his Tenant and a Robber to alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate the Landlord's right.</hi> It is the opinion of <hi>Grotius,</hi> l. 1. c. 4. ſ. 15. <hi>That the Acts of him that exerciſeth the power of the Empire, have the vertue of obliging the Subject, not by any authority of his own, which is none, but becauſe it is probable, that he who hath the right of Government, had rather have the coommands of the Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour's to be valid, than that the Laws and Juſtice being ſuſpended, Confuſion ſhould follow. See</hi> Grotius <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 6. <hi>ſ.</hi> 5. <hi>And it is to be preſumed, that every Prince hath ſo much Humanity, that he would rather have his Subjects preſerved by whatſoever means, then by ſtriving in vain, and ſhewing their impotent affections out of ſeaſon, to be deſtroyed without any good effect; Compare</hi> 2 Sam. 15.25, 26. <hi>and</hi> 1 Kings 3.26. <hi>Thus in</hi> Livy, <hi>The</hi> Romans <hi>being deſired by the</hi> Petellines <hi>to give them aſſiſtance, declared, that they could not protect them who were ſo remote from them, adviſing them to return home and conſult for their own ſafety. See alſo the Oration of</hi> Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nand, <hi>flying out of</hi> Naples, <hi>in</hi> Guittardin, <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>near the end: In this caſe nothing appears more probable, than that if the lawful Prince be reduced to ſuch a condition that he cannot afford ſuch defence to his Subjects as he ought, and the ſtrength of his Subjects is not ſo great as to reſiſt the Invader, without evident deſtruction, it may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed that the expelled Prince doth ſo long releaſe the obligation of his
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:63211:22"/>
Subjects until there be a way opened for the regaining his Kingdom, and ſuch as is neceſſary for their preſervation, and to avoid deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; and thus far only the Faith promiſed to the Invader ſeems to oblige. So that this Faith is only temporary and expires when the lawful Prince hath an opportunity to recover his right: And this Faith proceeds not from any intrinſical obligation of the Conſcience, which is under a preſent fear. See</hi> Grotius <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>ſ.</hi> 6. <hi>Yet where an external Right and Dominion is admitted, I ſee no cauſe why an external Obligation, which doth not touch the Conſcience, may not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be admitted:</hi> See 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 11. 2 <hi>Cron.</hi> 23. on which place <hi>Hobbs</hi> rightly obſerves, that <hi>Athaliah</hi> was juſtly caſt out of the Government, not by any right that the Prieſt had, as a Prieſt, but in right of the Child that was to ſucceed as King. All which things being conſidered, there is ſcarce any caſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in private men may oppoſe an unjuſt Poſſeſſour of an Empire, eſpecially conſidering (what experience doth ſhew <hi>(viz.)</hi> that by ſuch Conſpiracies the Invader is more exaſperated to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the people. See <hi>Juſtine</hi> l. 16. c. 5. at the end.</p>
               <p>The only thing conſiderable in this Diſcourſe is, whether ſuch Subjects as have been deſerted and left in confuſion by their King, are bound to reſerve and pay their Allegiance to him in caſe he ſhould return, or whether they are bound by their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Oaths to aſſiſt him in the recovery of his Dominions? To which I anſwer, That the caſe ſeems much like, as if a man living in a City among his innocent Neighbours, ſhould ſet his own Houſe on fire intending thereby to deſtroy his Neighbours Houſes, and though he flyes for this fact, yet ſtill imploys his Agents and Boutefeus to continue that fire to an utter deſtruction of the whole City: Whether are the Citizens in reaſon or conſcience obliged to receive ſuch an ill Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, or to confide in him? The reſolution of this caſe, will be a good anſwer to the Doubt propoſed, of which I ſhall ſpeak more hereafter.</p>
               <p>As to the Original of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government, it is evident, that the <hi>Saxons,</hi> who ſubdued the <hi>Britains,</hi> were deſcended of the <hi>Germans,</hi> who were governed by ſuch Kings as had their <hi>Comites, (i. e.)</hi> Counts or Companions who were to hear and determine the Grievances of the people, complained of againſt their Kings: and <hi>Edgar</hi> the Firſt was choſen by ſuch Counts to be their Monarch, and to defend the Rights of the people, as <hi>Wigonienſis</hi> p. 355. Nor can it be thought conſiſtent with the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:63211:22"/>
Divine Goodneſs and Wiſdom, that he ſhould ever ſet up ſuch an order of Men (their corruptions and paſſions being conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered) as ſhould have an uncontrolable power to kill and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy whom and as many as they pleaſed, the end of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being the Welfare of the people, and the Magiſtrate being appointed to be the Miniſter of God for the peoples good.</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Orlando Bridgman,</hi> in his Speech to the Grand Jury of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> p. 12, 13. ſays, <hi>That the Crown of</hi> England <hi>is an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Crown, as depending on no Earthly Potentate but on God one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; yet it is not ſo Abſolute</hi> (ſays he) <hi>but that the Subjects, as to their Properties, Liberties, and Laws, have as good a right as the King.</hi> And Sir <hi>Tho. Smith,</hi> Privy Counſellor to Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> diſtinguiſheth between the Conceſſions which the King makes, <hi>That they are either of Right or of Grace:</hi> The way of asking any thing in Parliament is by Petition, yet the Petition of Right in K. <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, ſhews that the people had a right to the things they petitioned for; and they have undoubtedly a right to petition for the confirmation of their Rights when they have been invaded; and hence it is that <hi>Bracton,</hi> l. 1. c. 17. ſays, <hi>Superiores habet Rex Deum &amp; legem per quam factus eſt Rex item Curiam ſuam Comites &amp; Barones qui cùm viderint Regem ſine fraeno fraenum ſibi ponere tenenter.</hi> And Chancellour <hi>Forteſcue</hi> tells <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. <hi>That the King cannot alter the Laws of his Kingdom, for he governs his People not only by a Regal but a Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Power; when it is ſaid the Princes Will hath the force of a Law, this</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is to be underſtood of a Regal or Abſolute Power, from which a Political Power much differs, for ſuch can neither change the Law, nor charge the People with new Impoſitions againſt their Wills.</hi> And <hi>Bracton,</hi> l. 1. c. 2. <hi>Leges Anglicanae cum fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint approbatae, &amp; Regis Sacramento confirmatae mutari non pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint;</hi> and he adds, <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 17. <hi>Temperent ergo Reges, Reges po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam ſuam per legem quae eſt fraenum potentiae,</hi> Let Kings there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reſtrain their Power by the Law, which is the Bridle of their Power; and <hi>l.</hi> 1. c. 8. <hi>Rex in juſtitiâ recipiendâ minimo de populo comparatur.</hi> The King in receiving Judgment is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the meaneſt of his People. <hi>Claudius Seſil</hi> a <hi>French</hi> Hiſtorian ſays as much of their Kings, <hi>That the Parliament was ſet as a Bridle to him, though they have now caſt it off.</hi> Judge <hi>Jenkins</hi> ſays to this purpoſe, <hi>We do hold only what the Law holds.</hi> The King's Prerogative, and the Peoples Liberties are both
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:63211:23"/>
determined by Law; and <hi>Charles</hi> the 1ſt in his Declaration at <hi>York,</hi> ſays, <hi>That his Prerogatives are built on the Laws of the Land:</hi> And when the Parliament would have him grant an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Power to the Lords Lieutenants, he tells them in his Anſwer to both Houſes, <hi>That if they would have him to grant more Power to thoſe Lieutenants, than by the Law of the Land was in the King himſelf, it was fit that the ſame ſhould be by ſome Law firſt veſted in him with a Power to transfer it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And Judge <hi>Jenkins</hi> ſays, (ſpeaking of the Oath of Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy) <hi>We do not ſwear that the King is above all Law, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the ſafety of the People; but his Majeſty and we will ſwear to the contrary, the Law and Safety of the People are his Honour, Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Strength.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the Objection made from the Declaration, viz. <hi>That it is not lawful on any pretence to take Armes againſt the King,</hi> &amp;c. from the Statute 13 of <hi>Ch.</hi> 2d, c. 6. <hi>That it is unlawful for the Parliament to levy War offenſive or defenſive againſt the King.</hi> Thô that be not much to their caſe who did not take up Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, or thoſe that were duly commiſſioned by him: There is a full anſwer given by the Earl of <hi>Clarendon,</hi> to Mr. <hi>Hobbs,</hi> who extended the King's power beyond the Law, <hi>In dangerous circumſtances</hi> (ſays he) <hi>men are not to reſort ſo much to the words of Submiſſion, as to the intention of the Lawgivers, which could not be, that the Prince ſhould have power to take away the lives of his innocent Subjects, nor could ſuch a Submiſſion be ever ſuppoſed to be the mind of the Contractors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For ſuppoſe that the late King had come armed with ſome <hi>Iriſh Papiſts</hi> into the Houſe, while that <hi>Parliament</hi> ſate, with a purpoſe to deſtroy them, would they tamely have ſubmitted, and kept their Swords by their ſides, when the Swords of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> were aimed at their Throats? If ſuch a caſe had been propoſed, they would never have made ſuch a Law as ſhould be written in their bloud; and therefore that Law muſt have ſome other interpretation, ſuch as this, That a Defence againſt illegal actions committed by perſons that are not qualified by Law, is not levying War againſt the King: for if any one, or many be ſent to take away my life without a due Trial, he is not ſent by the King, for the Law is the King's autoritive Command, and that alloweth me a fair Trial for my life, which if it be denied, I may and ought to defend it againſt all ſuch as come to take it away contrary to Law. And the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:63211:23"/>
                  <hi>Magna Charta</hi> declares ſuch Commiſſions to be null, where the words are, <hi>That neither we,</hi> (i. e.) <hi>the King, nor our Heirs ſhall procure or do any thing whereby the Liberties hereby granted ſhall be infringed, and if any ſuch thing be procured, it ſhall be of no force.</hi> Now the Liberty granted <hi>Ch.</hi> 1. of that Charter, is, That no man ſhould be puniſhed or condemned but by Trial; <hi>Per Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentum proborum &amp; legalium hominum de vireneto;</hi> that is, by a Jury of honeſt and lawful men of the Neighbourhood: And this priviledge was purchaſed by the fifteenth part of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects Goods, and ſo becomes their Inheritance; it is <hi>Libertas multoties empta:</hi> If we may reſiſt a perſon that is not qualified by Law, though he act a thing that is juſt, much more when a perſon that is not qualified comes to act an unjuſt thing; for no man can want authority to defend his life againſt him who wants authority to take it away. And not to reſiſt in ſuch a caſe, is not only againſt the Law of Nature, but againſt our own Law, which always intends the good of innocent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; but ſuch a Law would deſtroy the foundation of all our other Laws, and the Government itſelf, for it would turn a Limited into an Abſolute Monarchy.</p>
               <p>To make a Commiſſion valid, firſt the perſon that grants it muſt have juſt authority. 2dly, The perſon commiſſioned muſt be legally qualified. 3dly, It muſt be for the execution of a lawful action; and <hi>malum ex quolibet de fectu,</hi> the want of any of theſe renders the Commiſſion illegal; for the King himſelf hath no authority to grant Commiſſions againſt the rules of the Law, for the executing of his own Will; nor can any one execute ſuch a Commiſſion without Law, but he is in danger of being judged by the Law: And hence it is, that the Acts of <hi>Pardon</hi> and <hi>Indemnity</hi> are extended to ſuch as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt and Second, acted by legal Commiſſions, becauſe they might have done in the heat of War, what might have been judged Criminal in times of Peace.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf was much moved, and ſhewed a kind of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance when he was but gently at the Command of the high Prieſt, becauſe it was contrary to Law: And Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> in his practical Caſes, <hi>Decad.</hi> 2. <hi>Caſe</hi> the Firſt, ſays, <hi>If a Thief rob me of my Treaſure and flies, my Conſcience would not ſtrike me if I purſue him, and ſo ſtrike him that he dies;</hi> and our Law hath provided for the indemnity of ſuch as ſlay another <hi>ſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendendo,</hi> as in the Caſe of <hi>Simpſon,</hi> mentioned by Sir
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:63211:24"/>
                  <hi>Edward Cook</hi> in the fourth part of his Reports, <hi>p.</hi> 333. when one would have ſeized him and carried him away, was ſlain in the Attempt by <hi>Simpſon;</hi> it was adjudged to be done in his own Defence, and found a chance medley, and <hi>Simpſon</hi> was acquitted: And by the like Reaſon, if a multitude of Armed Men that have no Authority, or are not qualified by Law, do aſſault me to take away my Life, or my Goods, I may reſiſt them; and as every Conſtable in caſe of an unlawful Riot, hath power to ſuppreſs the Riotous perſons, ſo hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very private perſon againſt ſuch perſons as aſſault him contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Law, and <hi>a fortiori</hi> much more a Community of Lords and Commons againſt an Army not qualified according to Law.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Sheringham</hi> who moſt rationally defended the Power of our Kings, doth grant, <hi>That thoſe Laws which are made for the benefit of the Prince and People are fundamental, and cannot be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered without the Ruin of the whole Building; if therefore any Law or Declaration in favour of the Prince againſt the People, or of the People againſt the Prince ſhall be made, it deſtroys the fundamental Laws, and is invalid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Among the Laws of King <hi>Edward,</hi> c. 17. <hi>De Regis Officio,</hi> The Liberties of the People being mentioned, it is ſaid, <hi>That the King is conſtituted for the preſervation of them,</hi> which if he do not, <hi>neo nomen Regis in eo conſtabit,</hi> he ſhall not retain the Name of a King: And <hi>Bracton</hi> ſays, <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 24. <hi>Eſt enim Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Regis facere Juſtitiam &amp; Judicium pacem tenere, ſine quibus conſiſtere non poteſt nec tenere, (i. e.)</hi> The Crown of the King is to do Juſtice and Judgment, to preſerve Peace, without which he cannot ſubſiſt; and to this purpoſe is that which <hi>Matthew Paris</hi> mentioneth, fol. 563. of the <hi>London</hi> Edition, <hi>Comites Ceſtriae Gladium Sancti Edwardi qui Curtain dicitur ante regem bauclantes in ſignum quod Comes Palatinus regem ſi oberret habet de jure poteſtatem coercendi,</hi> That the Earls of <hi>Cheſter</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried a Sword which was called <hi>Curtain</hi> before the King, to ſignifie that when the King did err that Earl had a Power to reſtrain him; and that Parliament that depoſed <hi>Richard</hi> the 2d did refer to a known Statute, which they told him was not long ſince put in practice, whereby it was provided, <hi>That if the King through a fooliſh Obſtinacy and contempt of his People, or any other irregular way ſhould alienate himſelf from his People, and would not govern by the Laws of his Kingdom made by the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:63211:24"/>
Lords of the Kingdom, but ſhould exerciſe his own Will; from thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth it was lawful for them with the conſent of the People to depoſe him from the Crown:</hi> Which Law was not denied, nor indeed is it extant <hi>totidem verbis,</hi> though it be implied in the Charter of King <hi>John,</hi> where Liberty was granted the Lords and Commons in ſuch caſes to ſeize his Dominions, and only to take care of the Perſons of the King and Queen in a private Capacity. And by the 24th Article againſt that King, it was alledged, <hi>That he had cauſed the Records and Rolls concerning the State of the Government to be erazed and embezelled to the great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment of the People, and diſheriſon of the Crown.</hi> And the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, of the <hi>Mirror,</hi> p. 8. ſpeaking of the riſe of our Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, ſays, <hi>That when</hi> 40 <hi>Princes choſe one King to Reign over them, to govern the People of God, and to maintain the Chriſtian Faith, and defend their Goods and Perſons in quiet, by the rules of Right, and to be obedient to the rules of Right; if he did not ſo, he ſhould looſe the Name of a King.</hi> Theſe things are ſufficient to prove an Original Contract, ſo fundamental that no future Statute can abrogate it.</p>
               <p>For the Common-wealth is ſtill in the condition of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor that cannot be forced to ſtand to Laws made againſt its own benefit: And <hi>Conſtantinus Leo</hi> in the <hi>Bizantine</hi> Hiſtory, ſays, <hi>That the end of a King is the general good, which if he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form not, be is but the counterfeit of a King:</hi> And <hi>Theodoſius Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior</hi> in the <hi>Inſtitute,</hi> l. 1. <hi>Titul.</hi> 24. ſays, <hi>The Prince is bound to the Laws on which his Authority depends, and to the Laws he ought to ſubmit:</hi> And ſubmitted they have, not only ſince the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Kings came to the Crown, but long before, as hath been ſhewn; which Oaths do as much bind the Conſciences of the Kings, as of the People, and ſo it hath and muſt be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged notwithſtanding any Diſpenſation of the Pope to the contrary; it was a good King that ſaid, <hi>He ſhall not aſcend to God's Holy Hill that keepeth not his Oath and Promiſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For by an Oath Gods Honour is given as an Hoſtage for the performance, and though a King were ſurpriſed in giving ſuch an Oath, as <hi>Joſhua</hi> was by the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> yet is he bound to the performance, and ſo it ſeems are his Succeſſors; for when <hi>Saul</hi> acted contrary to the Oath of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> God avenged it on him, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21, 12. Old <hi>Fleta</hi> ſpeaking of the King's Oath, ſays, <hi>Ipſe ad hoc ſpecialiter ex virtute Sacramenti obligatur, &amp; ideo Corona inſignitur ut per judicia populum ſibi commiſſum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:63211:25"/>
                  <hi>Tho. Walſingham</hi>'s Hiſt. Angl. <hi>p.</hi> 193. relates the Coronation of <hi>Richard</hi> the 2d, that the Archbiſhop with the Marſhal of <hi>England</hi> going before him, declares to the People from one part of the Scaffolds to another, that the King had taken the Oath, and asks them if they would conſent to have him their King and Liege-Lord, to which they Anſwer, <hi>they would;</hi> the breaking this Oath was one great Article againſt him. And 15 of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3d <hi>Stat.</hi> 1. <hi>We conſidering how by a Bond of our Oath we be bound to the obſervance and defence of the Laws and Cuſtoms of the Realm,</hi> and in the 20th of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3d 'tis expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed more largely, <hi>We perceiving that the Law of the Land which we by our Oath be bound to maintain is the leſs well kept, and the Execution of the ſame diſturbed, we greatly moved in Conſcience in this matter, deſiring as much for the Pleaſure of God, and Eaſe of our Subjects, as to ſave our Conſcience, and to keep our ſaid Oath,</hi> the like is in the Statute of <hi>Proviſors;</hi> ſo in 3. <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. <hi>The King,</hi> ſays he, <hi>was bound by Oath to paſs a new Bill brought to him againſt Extortion,</hi> 6. Hen. 6. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>By reaſon of our Rega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity we be bounden to the ſafeguard of our Kingdom.</hi> So that how light ſoever the late King eſteemed his Coronation Oath, theſe ancient Kings in thoſe dark times of Popery, thought themſelves ſtrictly bound to the performance of them; and the Nobles did retain ſo much Power in their hands, as to enforce their Kings to the obſervation of them. King <hi>James</hi> told his Parliament <hi>March</hi> 21. 1609. <hi>That the King is bound by a double Oath to preſerve the Laws tacitly, as being King, and ſo bound to protect his People and the Laws, and expreſly by his Coronation Oath: So as every juſt King is bound to obſerve that Paction made with his People by his Laws, framing the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereunto; and a King leaves to be a King, and degenerates into a Tyrant, as ſoon as he leaves off to govern by Law, in which caſe the King's Conſcience may ſpeak to him, as the poor Woman to</hi> Philip <hi>of</hi> Macedon, <hi>either govern according to Law, or ceaſe to be King.</hi> And elſewhere he ſaid, <hi>If he ſhould not keep the Laws to which he was Sworn, he ſhould be Perjured.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And by what reaſon can a man be obliged to obſerve his Oath to a perſon that being mutual obliged to him, hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly violated his Oath, and becomes a perjur'd Perſon; it is well reſolved by <hi>Ameſius de Juramento,</hi> l. 4. c. 22. <hi>Quum aufertur ratio Juramenti, Juramentum ceſſat ratione eventus, Qui eaſus eſt eorum qui Juraverunt ſe obedituros domino aut prinoipi a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieui
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:63211:25"/>
qui poſtea ceſſat eſſe talis.</hi> When the reaſon of an Oath doth ceaſe, the obligation of the Oath ceaſeth alſo, by reaſon of the event, which is the caſe of ſuch who have ſworn to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey a Lord or Prince, who afterward ceaſeth to be ſo.</p>
               <p>King <hi>John</hi>'s Confirmation of an Original Contract. <hi>Anno</hi> 1214. upon granting the great Charter, and that of the <hi>Foreſt,</hi> it was enacted at <hi>Running-Mead, That</hi> 25 <hi>Barons ſhould be elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as Conſervators of the Liberties thereby granted, who upon Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of them might (no redreſs being made within 40 days after notice) enforce the King by ſeizing his Caſtles and Lands, and as a Security, the four chief Captains of the Caſtles of</hi> Northampton, Kenelworth, Nottingham, <hi>and</hi> Scarborough <hi>were ſworn to the Barons, and that none ſhould be placed in them, but ſuch as the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons thought to be faithful; and alſo the Caſtles of</hi> Rocheſter <hi>and others which of right belonged to the Archbiſhop of</hi> Canterbury <hi>were delivered up, and others to the Barons.</hi> But the King by help of ſome Forreigners regain'd them all, and was Maſter of all <hi>England,</hi> except the City of <hi>London,</hi> whoſe Suburbs he burnt. And then the Biſhops and Barons ſwore at St. <hi>Edmonds</hi> on the high Altar, <hi>That if King</hi> John <hi>did not obſerve his Grants, they would compel him to it by withholding their Allegiance, and ſeizing his Caſtles;</hi> and when the King would not reſtore their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Properties, they raiſe an Army under <hi>Robert Fitz-Walker,</hi> and regain all their Caſtles, enter <hi>London,</hi> and reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved never to deſiſt until their Charters were better ſecured. The King being generally forſaken, having not above ſeven Knights with him, whereas the Barons and Knights were reckoned 2000. beſides Eſquires of good Note: He ſent to the King of <hi>Morocco,</hi> offering the Kingdom to him, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving enquired into the difference between the King and his People, deſpiſed the offer, as <hi>Matthew Paris</hi> relates it. He offered it alſo to Pope <hi>Innocent,</hi> to be made Tributary to him, if he would excommunicate the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and the Barons, that he might be revenged on them; all which notwithſtanding they maintain the War, and they elect <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>France</hi> for their King, and their Actions were approved by the Peers of <hi>France</hi> aſſembled at <hi>Lyons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have read, that in the Clauſe of the Charter confirm'd by <hi>H.</hi> 3. it was provided, <hi>that if the King ſhould invade thoſe Rights, it was lawful for the Kingdom to riſe against him and do him what injury they could, as owing him no Allegiance.</hi> And much
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:63211:26"/>
to this purpoſe is quoted out of King <hi>John</hi>'s Charter in theſe words, <hi>Et illi Barones cum communa totius terrae deſtringent &amp; gravabunt nos modis omnibus quibus poterint ſcilicet per captionem Caſtrorum terrarum poſſeſſionem &amp; aliis modis donec fuerit emanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſecundum arbitrium eorum.</hi> And the practice of the Nobles and Commons in thoſe days do evidence, that they had ſome ſuch Grants from their Kings for their juſtification, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps much more then doth now appear; for it was made an Article againſt <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, <hi>that he had erazed and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bezled the Records, to the great dammage of the People, and the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inheriſon of the Crown.</hi> But this King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, upon a grant of the thirtieth part of his Subjects Goods, ratified their Charters, and Swore to preſerve them inviolably, as he was a Man, a Chriſtian, and a King, crowned and anointed; and the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> with the other Biſhops, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced a Sentence of Excommunication againſt all ſuch as ſhould invalidate the Priviledges granted by the Charters, throwing down on the ground the lighted Candles which were in their hands, and ſaying, <hi>So let every one who incurs this Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, be extinct in Hell.</hi> And here I cannot forbear to repeat that Article of the <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> which yet appears in the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Grant or Confirmation, which the Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> ſays, he hath in his own hands, under the great Seal, (<hi>See the Biſhop of</hi> Sarum<hi>'s Paſtoral Letter,</hi> p. 27.) whereby it is provided, <hi>That in caſe the King ſhould violate any part of the Charter, and ſhould refuſe to rectifie what be had done amiſs, it ſhould be lawful for the Barons and the whole People of</hi> England, <hi>to diſtreſs him by all the ways they could think on, ſuch as the ſeizing on his Caſtles, Lands and Poſſeſſions, proviſion being only made for the ſafety of the perſons of the King and Queen and their Children.</hi> Now this being a fundamental Law and Contract, and never repealed, may abundantly juſtifie all that hath been done by the People of <hi>England</hi> in the late Revolution. For whereas it is objected, that the late Laws and Declaration, <hi>That it is not lawful on any pretence whatſoever, to take up Arms: and that it is unlawful for both Houſes of Parliament to levy. War offenſive or defenſive against the King, and the Recognition made the first of King</hi> James, <hi>do ſuperſede all former Laws;</hi> I anſwer, That ſuch fundamental Laws cannot be abrogated, without a particular recital of them, and an expreſs abrogation; ſo that thoſe Laws mentioned in the Charters for the reſtraint of illegal Actions, and thoſe that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:63211:26"/>
gave the <hi>Heretochs</hi> the power of the Militia, and Officers by Sea and Land, not being particularly repealed, cannot be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogated by thoſe haſty Acts which have been ſince made; for though the Militia be by thoſe haſty Acts granted to the King, yet it muſt be underſtood, that they were ſo granted in truſt and confidence that it ſhould be imployed for the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and ſafety of the People; and Sir <hi>Edward Cooke</hi> in his Inſtitutes, on <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> alloweth, that the King hath no power over the Militia, to Muſter his Subjects, but only in ſuch caſes and in ſuch manner as the Parliament by ſpecial Acts hath preſcribed; and therefore thoſe <hi>Heretochs</hi> or Lord-Lieutenants which had the power of the Militia, for the word <hi>Heretoch,</hi> by <hi>Selden</hi> in his <hi>Titles of Honour,</hi> p. 603. is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of <hi>Here,</hi> which ſignifies <hi>Exercitus,</hi> and <hi>Togen ducere</hi> ſignifies <hi>Dux exercitus ſive navalis ſive terreſtris,</hi> and ſignifies a Commander of an Army by Sea or Land. See <hi>Spelman,</hi> p. 232, 348.</p>
               <p>That the Sheriffs of every County who had the <hi>Poſſe Comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatus,</hi> or the power of raiſing the Militia, were to be choſen by the People in the County-Courts, is evident by expreſs words of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor's Laws, <hi>Cap. de Herotochiis,</hi> as <hi>Lambard</hi>'s <hi>Arch.</hi> p. 135. and Sir <hi>Edward Cooke,</hi> 3 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 17, 19. And by the Articles againſt <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, charging him, <hi>that he put out divers Sheriffs elected by the Freeholders, and put in his own Favourites, ſubverting the Laws contrary to his own Oath and Honor.</hi> And <hi>Anno</hi> 1261. the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons by vertue of an Ordinance of Parliament made at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> 45. <hi>H.</hi> 3. made Sheriffs in divers Counties, and called them Guardians of the Counties, diſcharging them whom the King had made. <hi>Novos repulere virilitur Vicecomites.</hi> And in the 28th of <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. <hi>ch.</hi> the King granteth to the People, as of right, <hi>that they ſhall have the Election of the Sheriffs.</hi> And <hi>ch.</hi> 13. <hi>for as much as the King hath granted to the Commons the Election of She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs, the King wills, that they ſhall chuſe ſuch Sheriffs that ſhall not charge them,</hi> &amp;c. And Sir <hi>Edward Cooke,</hi> on <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> proves, <hi>p.</hi> 147. <hi>&amp;c. that the right of electing Sheriffs was anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently in the People, as it was and is in</hi> London, York, Briſtol, Gloceſter, <hi>and in all great Cities which are Counties, and in</hi> Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſex. And generally all the great Officers of the Kingdom were choſen in Parliament. So were the <hi>Heretoches</hi> or Lord-Lieutenants in every County choſen by a full <hi>Folkemote</hi> in every
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:63211:27"/>
County of the Realm. And it is evident throughout our Hiſtories, that the Kings of <hi>England</hi> never did or could raiſe or maintain a War without the conſent and aid of their Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments. <hi>Anno</hi> 1242. <hi>Henry</hi> the Third ſummoned a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, requiring their aid for a War againſt <hi>France,</hi> to which he had ſworn for recovering of his Rights, but they anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>That they would grant no Aids, nor make any War, till the Truce with</hi> France <hi>was expired;</hi> and though he cloſeted the Nobles one by one, and by perſuaſions and threats ſought to ingage them, yet they anſwered, <hi>That they admired, that without their Counſel and Conſent, he would undertake ſo difficult buſineſs.</hi> So that unleſs the Nation by their late Acts did intend to deſtroy all their ancient Rights and Liberties, we cannot ſuppoſe it to be their ſence, but that their General Rules might admit of ſome Exceptions and Reſtraints.</p>
               <p>Suppoſe a King, perſuaded by Evil Counſellors and detain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them, do break his Solemn Oaths, raiſeth a War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Kingdom, for ſubverſion of the Laws and in defence of ſuch Counſellors as perſuaded him thereunto, do appear in their Army where his perſon is in danger, whether may the Subjects raiſe Arms and fight againſt ſuch an Army wherein the King is perſonally ingaged. <hi>Anſw.</hi> This was the Caſe of <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, who, with his Son Prince <hi>Edward,</hi> was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Priſoner in the Battel of <hi>Lewis</hi> by the Earl of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> who, to countenance his deſigns, carried him about as a Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; whereupon the Nobles raiſed an Army, and in the Battel of <hi>Eveſham</hi> ſlew the Earl, and the King himſelf was wounded nigh to death, as <hi>Matth. Paris</hi> relates, yet in a Parliament at <hi>Wincheſter, Anno</hi> 1266. the Earl and his Army were adjud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Traytors and Rebels, and the Nobles and their Army were rewarded.</p>
               <p>If the Owner of a Park grant to a Keeper a Leaſe thereof for Life, the Condition, though it be not expreſs'd, yet by Law is this, that if he ſuffer the Deer to be killed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed through his neglect, or their Paſture eaten up, he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiteth his Grant, in the judgment of the Common Law. And though ſuch a Keeper, to preſerve his Deer, do wound or kill the Robber, he is held guiltleſs by a Statute of 21 <hi>E.</hi> 1. as <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtal</hi> of <hi>Forreſts,</hi> 19. and <hi>Stamford</hi>'s Pleas, <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 5, 6. Doth the Law take care for Beaſts, and not for Subjects, and are not theſe much better than they, or their Goods, Liberties, and Properties, than the Graſs for Deer?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:63211:27"/>Some Kings have been ſo hardy as to ingage themſelves in ſingle Tilts and Combats with their Subjects, to ſhew their Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, as <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth did in the ſixteenth Year of his Reign, againſt the Earl of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> wherein the King was like to be ſlain; and <hi>Henry</hi> the Second of <hi>France, Anno</hi> 1559. was ſlain in a Juſt by the Earl of <hi>Montgomery</hi> his Subject, whoſe Spear pierced through his Eye to the Brain; but theſe being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked thereunto by their Kings, were not adjudged Traytors, having no deſign of evil againſt their Kings. So that if a Prince voluntary ingage himſelf in an unneceſſary Combate with his Subjects, and they in defence of their Laws, Liberties, and Lives, do chance (not intentionally) wound or ſlay their Prince, I ſee not but they are as excuſable as the others, the blame lyeth on the wilful aſſaulter, and not on them that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelves. <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, King of <hi>France,</hi> fell di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted in the head of his Army, and ſlew ſome of his Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers; whereupon they diſarmed him, and kept him cloſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner as a <hi>Bedlam,</hi> till he was recovered, nor were any que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned as Traytors for ſo doing: The Caſe ſeems not much unlike to that of <hi>Walter Terril,</hi> who ſhooting at a Deer, by a a caſual glance of the Arrow, ſlew the King, <hi>William Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus in caſes of Manſlaughter, when one kills another <hi>ſe defendendo,</hi> a Pardon by Law is granted of courſe. It appears, that <hi>David</hi> offered to aſſiſt the King of <hi>Achiſh</hi> in his Wars a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Saul,</hi> wherein <hi>Saul</hi> was ſlain, by which it may alſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that an oppreſſed Subject may aſſiſt a Prince that gives him protection in a lawful War againſt his oppreſſing Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, though the Soveraigns life be in hazard of being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed in that War. This will appear in the Caſe of <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>David.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saul</hi> was Father-in-Law to <hi>David,</hi> who was appointed by God to ſucceed him in due time, for which cauſe among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers it is probable that <hi>Saul</hi> hated him, eſpecially becauſe the People extolled <hi>David</hi> above him; <hi>Saul</hi> hath ſlain his thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, and <hi>David</hi> his ten thouſands, and ſought occaſion to ſlay him, and to make void his Right of Succeſſion, of the Truth whereof <hi>David</hi> being informed by <hi>Jonathan,</hi> he got about four hundred Men as a Life Guard; ſeeing he could not confide in the Promiſes of <hi>Saul,</hi> and <hi>Abiathar</hi> the high Prieſt, complained of the Tyranny of <hi>Saul,</hi> that he had commanded
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:63211:28"/>
the Prieſts of God to be ſlain upon the Accuſation of <hi>Doeg,</hi> and <hi>David</hi> entertains <hi>Abiathar,</hi> and ſuch as fled to him for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.23. <hi>Abide thou with me, fear not, for he that ſeeketh thy life, ſeeketh my life, but with me thou ſhalt be in ſafety.</hi> Hereupon he with his Men got into <hi>Keilah,</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> raiſeth his People to aſſault him; but <hi>David</hi> enquireth of the Lord, (intending no doubt to make reſiſtance againſt <hi>Saul</hi>) whether <hi>Saul</hi> would come againſt him, and whether the Men of <hi>Keilah</hi> would deliver him up to <hi>Saul,</hi> and being anſwered, that they would, he leaves <hi>Keilah,</hi> and flies into the Mountains, where, doubtleſs, if <hi>Saul</hi> had aſſaulted him, he would have defended himſelf; but being too weak, <hi>Saul</hi>'s Men being more than ſix to one, he roves up and down as he could, and to ſhew that he only ſought the defence of his own Life, not the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of <hi>Saul</hi>'s, he ſpared it twice, when it was in his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and was perſwaded by his Men to have taken it away, to whom he thus anſwers, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.10. <hi>The Lord ſhall ſmite him, or his day ſhall come to die, or he ſhall deſcend into battle and periſh, (i.e.)</hi> he will aſſault me, and may periſh in that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt which he wilfully attempting may be ſlain, and then I ſhall be innocent, but if I ſhould ſlay him in cold Bloud, and with an intention to deſtroy him, I ſhould be guilty; nor was <hi>David</hi> affrighted from joyning himſelf with the King of <hi>Achiſh</hi> in a Battle againſt <hi>Saul,</hi> in which Battle <hi>Saul</hi> periſhed, which was more than his ſelf-defence, that ſo <hi>Saul</hi>'s Army might be weakned, or diverted from the purſuit of him. Whence it follows, that although we hold the King's Perſon be inviolable, yet if he ſhall unjuſtly expoſe himſelf in a War to deſtroy his Subjects, they may juſtly raiſe an Army to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelves, and though the King ſhould caſually periſh, they are innocent. The Bleſſing pronounc'd by <hi>Amaſas</hi> on <hi>David,</hi> ſhews Gods approbation of his intended Defence, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12, 18.</p>
               <p>It follows alſo, that a Prince in ſuch a caſe as <hi>David</hi> was, may joyn himſelf with the Enemies of his oppreſſing Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, which, doubtleſs, will hold in the caſe of our preſent King's uniting himſelf with the confederate Proteſtant Princes in Defence of their Religion, Laws, and Liberties, which are in danger. <hi>Albericus Gentilis,</hi> Profeſſor of Civil Law in <hi>Oxford,</hi> under Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> diſtinguiſheth of a threefold lawful De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, 1. <hi>Neceſſary,</hi> 2. <hi>Profitable,</hi> 3. <hi>Honeſt;</hi> and ſays, <hi>He
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:63211:28"/>
is neceſſitated againſt whom an Enemy comes Armed, or prepares Arms, on which the War againſt</hi> Methridates <hi>was accounted juſt, becauſe of his preparations, which their Adverſaries accounted a more real Declaration of War than any words, Pia arma quibus nulla niſae in armis relinquitur ſpes:</hi> He who would keep himſelf out of Danger, muſt meet and prevent it, which is a point of greater Wiſdom and Courage, than to expect it and revenge it; it is alſo more ſafe and eaſie to prevent a future, than to redreſs a preſent Evil. <hi>Turpius ejicitur quam non admittitur Hoſtis:</hi> We preſently ſlay a Serpent at ſight, not ſtaying till he hurt us; and ſuffer not noxious Weeds or Thorns to grow up, but grub them up by the roots while they are young: if we expect the firſt ſtroke it may kill or diſable us; <hi>Venjenti oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currite morbo,</hi> is good advice to a body politick as well as na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural: If our Adverſary have declared his will, and is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring a power to hurt us, we may not carry to receive the firſt blow, but anticipate the evil, as <hi>Gladiators</hi> are wont to do: Yea, it hath been always practiſed, to put a ſtop to the ambition of great Monarchs, who have unjuſtly invaded one Man's Dominions, leſt he ſhould attempt the like upon others; and hence the Princes of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> have been careful to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve an equal balance between growing Empires, <hi>Poſſe nocere ſat eſt quod<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> poteſt alios perdere perde prior;</hi> We may as juſtly remove impendent evils, as thoſe that are actually befallen us. The whole World is but one great City, and tho ſome part of Mankind is nearer than others, yet our Charity ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to all; <hi>Si non homini tamen humanitati:</hi> Thus <hi>Baldus,</hi> and both Civilians and Canoniſts determine, That it is a fault to omit the defence of another, but of ourſelves a treachery. <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racides Eccl.</hi> 4. Free him to whom injury is done, out of the hand of the Injurious. <hi>Conſtantine</hi> ſays, <hi>We ought to account of the injuries done to others as our own.</hi> And if this be the duty of private men, much more of Princes; and if in the other caſes, much more in the caſe of Religion; Thus <hi>Juſtine</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the <hi>Perſians, That he ought to defend the Chriſtians, whom they would compel to forſake their Religion:</hi> Thus <hi>Conſtantine</hi> help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Chriſtians that were oppreſſed by <hi>Maxentius;</hi> and Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> aſſiſted the <hi>Hollanders</hi> againſt the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who ſought not only to deſtroy the Proteſtant Religion there, but having broken down that Pale of <hi>Europe,</hi> as <hi>Lipſius</hi> called it, they ſhould have extended their Tyranny farther. Dr. <hi>Ferne,</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:63211:29"/>
pleading the Cauſe of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, grants, <hi>That Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Defence againſt the ſudden Aſſaults of the King's Meſſengers if illegal, tho' the King be preſent, is lawful, even to warding of the King's blows, and to reſtrain his hands, and reſcue their innocent Brethren out of his hands, as the People did</hi> Jonathan <hi>from the hands of</hi> Saul. And if a King ſhould joyn with Robbers or Pirates by Land or Sea, the Subjects might lawfully defend themſelves, tho' the King were in their company.</p>
               <p>It is well known, that the Emperour, the Pope, and almoſt all the Princes in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> do joyn to prevent the ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Deſigns of the King of <hi>France,</hi> inſomuch, that they will rather aſſiſt <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> than ſuffer them to fall into the hands of the <hi>French:</hi> and if <hi>Popiſh Princes</hi> agree in this, for the preſervation of their Dominions from an ambitious and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring Monarch, tho' of their own Religion, much more may a <hi>Proteſtant Prince</hi> for the recovery of his own Right, and for the preſervation of the juſt Rights, Laws, Liberties, and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of his Allies and Confederates.</p>
               <p>Aeneas Sylvius, <hi>If a King contemn the Laws and Subjects all to his Luſt, will not the States in ſuch a caſe depoſe him and chuſe ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther who ſhall ſwear to govern by Law, as reaſon tells us it ought to be. Aquinas,</hi> ſpeaking of depoſing Tyrants, ſays, <hi>They are not guilty who do it, though obliged to them by Oath, for he deſerves the People ſhould not truſt him who tranſgreſſeth the Duty of a King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> The people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> might as well judge <hi>David</hi> to have abdicated his Kingdom, as the people of <hi>England</hi> King <hi>James,</hi> for great complaints were made againſt <hi>David</hi> by <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolom,</hi> concerning the Male-adminiſtration of Government, and his Adultery and Murther are in the Sacred Record, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, upon the approach of <hi>Abſolom</hi>'s Army he fled out of the Land. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> As to <hi>David</hi>'s perſonal miſcarriages, they were done in ſecret, ſcarce two or three made privy to thoſe deſigns; whence that expreſſion in <hi>Pſ.</hi> 51. <hi>Against thee only have I ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned;</hi> intimating, that it was not known to his people. So <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> told him, 2 Sam. 12.12. <hi>Thou didst it ſecretly, but I will do this before all Iſrael.</hi> And <hi>Uriah</hi> being dead, and his Wife con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting, there was none againſt whom <hi>David</hi> had ſinned, (as ſome do Comment) but theſe perſonal ſins did not make him obnoxious to the cenſures of his people: As for the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Kingdom, it was a forged Accuſation of <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:63211:29"/>
to ſteal the hearts of the people from his Father; for the Holy Ghoſt beareth witneſs to the contrary, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 78. <hi>ult. He fed them according to the integrity of his heart, and ruled them pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently with all his power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>Abſolom</hi>'s Conſpiracy was ſecret and a ſudden ſurprize, the men that followed him went in the ſimplicity of their hearts, not knowing the intended Rebellion. Beſides, the War againſt <hi>David</hi> was moſt unnaturally raiſed by <hi>Abſolom</hi> his Son and Subject, moved by his declared Ambition, 2 Sam. 15.4. <hi>O that I were made judge in the land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And altho' it be ſaid that <hi>David</hi> fled out of the Land; that was only for the convenience of his Army that came to his ſuccour, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.24. whom he conducted over <hi>Jordan</hi> to <hi>Mahanaim,</hi> a fortified City on the Borders, that had Walls and Gates; nor did his people deſert him, for he had a numerous Army, and great Commanders, Captains over Thouſands and over Hundreds; and with him were the Prieſts that carried the Ark; for whoſe ſafety <hi>David</hi> was eſpecially careful: and the Wood of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> where <hi>Abſolom</hi> was ſlain, and his Army defeated, was near to <hi>Jordan,</hi> and that part of the River ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry narrow, for <hi>David</hi> and his men ſpeedily paſt it over in Boats. And yet the people had a notion of ſetting <hi>Abſolom</hi> on the Throne in <hi>David</hi>'s abſence, that they might have Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice adminiſtred; for 2 Sam. 19.10. <hi>They had anointed Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom; and Huſhai among the reſt ſaluted him ſaying, God ſave the King,</hi> 2 Sam. 16.16. Yet <hi>David</hi> retained the hearts of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, for 2 Sam. 19.9. <hi>All the people were at ſtrife throughout all the tribes of Iſrael, ſaying, The King ſaved us from the hands of the Philiſtines, and delivered us from our enemies, and now he is fled before Abſolom.</hi> And <hi>Zadok</hi> and <hi>Abiathar</hi> the Prieſts prevailed with <hi>Amaſa</hi> to turn the hearts of all the men of <hi>Judah</hi> to King <hi>David,</hi> and as one man they invited him and all his Servants to return.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> If God ſend a wicked Prince for the puniſhment of the ſins of a people, it is their duty to ſubmit to the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their iniquities, as our Church Homelies inſtruct us; in theſe words, Homely the firſt, againſt Diſobedience, <hi>p.</hi> 280. <hi>For Subjects do deſerve through their ſins to have an evil Prince, and then to rebel againſt him were double and treble evil, by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking God more to plague them: Let us either deſerve to have a good Prince, or let us patiently ſuffer and obey ſuch as we deſerve;
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:63211:30"/>
and whether the Prince be good or evil, let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> according to the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures pray for him, for his continuance and increaſe in Goodneſs; if he be good, and for his amendment if he be evil;</hi> for, <hi>Reges quando boni muneris eſt Dei quando mali, ex merito populi.</hi> We may <hi>bonos Imperatores<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> expe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> quoſcunque c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lirare.</hi> So <hi>Taci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us</hi> ſays<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And <hi>we ought to indure wicked Princes as we do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> or Scarcity, which as of God's ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ing:</hi> for there being in Nature a Viciſſitude of Earthly things, good and evil ſucceeding each other, we muſt receive evil at the hands of God with as wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a ſubmiſſion as we do good things, and the return of good things will ſatisfy for our calm ſubmiſſion to evils, as God bleſſed the later end of <hi>Job</hi> by doubling all his injoyments, and as after a ſhort perſecution in the <hi>Marian</hi> days the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants enjoyed a long tranquility under Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> &amp;c. and as none can, ſo none ought to reſiſt the will of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> It muſt be granted, that there is no evil befals a City or a Nation, but it is the Lords doing either by his permiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or his commiſſion; but it is as certain, that God not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves of all that he permits to be done in the World: and when God doth afflict a people for their ſins, that which is done juſtly by himſelf by way of permiſſion, cannot be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the Agents for want of a Commiſſion.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly, God may puniſh a Nation by Fire, Famine, or Sword, yet it is the duty of ſuch as ſuffer under thoſe Judgments to pray againſt them, and by the known rule, <hi>Pro quibus orandum pro iis laborandum,</hi> they may uſe all lawful endeavours againſt them: If God permit Fire to deſtroy my Habitation, or Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to plunder me, it is juſt with God to deal lo with me; yet I may and ought to endeavour the quenching of that fire, and as I am able, to reſiſt thoſe Robbers; otherwiſe it would not be lawful for Chriſtians to fight againſt thoſe <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars</hi> which invade <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> for the deſtruction of their Religion, when, in reſpect to God, ſuch Invaſions are made for the puniſhment of their ſins, <hi>viz.</hi> their unchriſtian Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Corruptions of the Doctrine of Chriſtianity. And if ſuch a Prince as the King of <hi>France,</hi> meerly for his ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or for propagating his own Superſtition, ſhall invade the Dominions of <hi>Proteſtant Princes,</hi> or deſtroy thouſands of his own Subjects contrary to his own Edicts, may they not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelves againſt ſuch unjuſt Invaſions of their Rights and Religion? or at leaſt, may they not pray againſt them, or
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:63211:30"/>
flye from his furious attempts? And yet this is a degree of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting him.</p>
               <p>Yet the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath not been guilty of theſe misbehaviours in any of theſe reſpects, for as long as the late King continued among us, we continued to pray for him; and the whole Militia were at his command, had he thought fit to intruſt them.</p>
               <p>We followed the advice of <hi>Moſes,</hi> even when we had a Howl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Wilderneſs on the one ſide, and a Red-Sea on the other, to ſtand ſtill, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> to keep our ſtations and duties, waiting for God's ſalvation, who in due time ſent us a <hi>Joſhua,</hi> with whom were the Prieſts of the Lord, and the Ark of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, to whom the ſwelling ſtreams of <hi>Jordan</hi> gave way, and opened a paſſage, and gave us an entrance to our <hi>Canaan,</hi> not only by dry Land, but without ſhedding of Bloud; a Bleſſing greater than that vouchſafed to <hi>Iſrael:</hi> And ſhould we like <hi>Sampſon</hi> lye ſtill in a dead ſleep, and not ſhake off thoſe bonds (while we are able) by which the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> would have bound us, and ſported themſelves in our deſtruction? When St. <hi>Peter</hi> was impriſoned by <hi>Herod, Acts</hi> 12.7. God ſent an Angel at the Prayers of the Church which were made inceſſantly for him; at whoſe preſence his Chains fell off, and the firſt, ſecond and third Gates of the Priſon were opened, and the Angol <hi>bid him ariſe quickly and gird himſelf and follow him;</hi> which if St. <hi>Peter</hi> had not done, he had certainly been wanting to his own preſervation.</p>
               <p>The ſame Apology which <hi>David</hi> made for himſelf, may ſerve for the oppreſſed but peaceable Subjects of <hi>England,</hi> 1 Sam. 24.11.12. <hi>Moreover, my father, ſee the skirt of thy gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in my hand; for in that I cut off the skirt of thy robe, and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thee not, know thou and ſee, that there is neither evil nor tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion in my hands, and I have not ſinned againſt thee; yet thou himſelf my ſoul to take it. The Lord judge between me and thee; and the Lord avenge me of thee; but my hand ſhall not be upon thee.</hi> And <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. <hi>Saul</hi> ſaid to <hi>David, Thou art more righteous than I.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for <hi>Tacitus,</hi> though he were a Heathen, yet he was a very wiſe man, and well acquainted with the Conſtitution of the <hi>Roman</hi> Government; for by the <hi>Lew Regia,</hi> granted by the Senate to <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> it was declared, <hi>Quicquid per Epiſtolum ſtatuit cognoſcons decrevit aut pro edictum perpala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> eſto.</hi> And
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:63211:31"/>
                  <hi>Cicero, De Legibus Regio Imperio duo ſunto— Militiae ſummum jus habento nemini parento.</hi> So <hi>Dion</hi> of <hi>Auguſtus, That he was free and of Abſolute Authority; both over himſelf and over the Laws, for the Emperour is a Living Law, and commands as much by word as the Law doth by writing.</hi> But we are not under the Laws of the <hi>Romans, Turks,</hi> or <hi>Tartars.</hi> And if God ſhould for our ſins now, or had he in the late King's raign permitted the <hi>French</hi> King to invade us with his Dragoons, I doubt not but we might <hi>Vim vi repellere,</hi> reſiſt his Tyranny and Uſurpation. And as to the Proteſtants under Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> none of them were put to death until ſhe had procured a Parliament to make Laws againſt them, and then it was their Duty to ſubmit. And we are bound with all thankfulneſs to bleſs God who prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the late King from procuring ſuch a Parliament, and ſuch Sanguinary Laws which he had well nigh effected, to the Extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of our Religion, Laws and Liberties, and faſtning thoſe heavy Yoaks of Popery and Slavery on us and the Poſterities that were to ſucceed us: <hi>This was the Lord's doing, and as it is marvellous in our eyes,</hi> ſo it ought with all humble thankfulneſs to be acknowledg'd and accepted.</p>
               <p>But it is objected from Sir <hi>E. Cooke, That the Regal Authority is ſo inherent in the perſon of the King, that no ſeparation can be made; ſo that as long as he lives, our Allegiance is due to him and to no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Whatever that great Lawyer ſays, the Law ſays other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; for even while a rightful Prince is in poſſeſſion, the Law makes a difference between his private and his publick Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city; and as while the King acts by the Laws, we owe him our Obedience; ſo in thoſe things wherein he acts arbitrarily by his own Will, contrary to Law, our Allegiance is not due in ſuch caſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> We are ſworn to the King and to his lawful Heirs and Succeſſors: now as the King while he lives can have no Heir to whom, in his life time, we owe our ſworn Allegiance, ſo when he dies, there can be no lawful Succeſſor but the Heir, if there be any that ſurvives.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> In the ſence of the Oath, there can be no Heir till the death of the King; and in our caſe there is no obligation due from our Oaths to the Heir, until he or ſhe be actually King or Queen of <hi>England,</hi> as our Law expounds itſelf. And when the King dies in a natural or civil and political ſence, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:63211:31"/>
his Government, and going over to an avowed Enemy to the Nation, their Religion and Liberties, or hath ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his Kingdom to the Uſurpations of the <hi>Pope,</hi> and ſo ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders himſelf not only as uſeleſs as if he were buried in a Cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, but as deſtructive as an open Enemy, there is in ſuch caſes a Demiſe made of the Crown, and it deſcends to the Heir.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly, In this caſe, if he that is not the next Heir by Bloud, be by the unanimous conſent of the people, as well as by the good liking of the lawful Heir, choſen and admitted into the actual poſſeſſion of the Government, all Rights that were due to the Heir, become due to ſuch a Succeſſor in the eye of the Law: So <hi>Bracton</hi> determins it, <hi>Heredis verbo omnes ſignificari ſucceſſores &amp; ſi verbis non ſint expreſſi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So <hi>Littleton</hi> in his <hi>Tenures, Title of Homage,</hi> Sect. 85. <hi>Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is due to every one</hi> (in poſſeſſion) <hi>that becomes King, and to no other.</hi> Judge <hi>Popham</hi> in his <hi>Reports,</hi> f. 16, 17. mentions a Caſe to this purpoſe: <hi>Richard</hi> the Third granted certain <hi>Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges</hi> to the City of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> with a <hi>Salvo</hi> to his Heirs; in Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s reign it was queſtioned, whether the <hi>Salvo</hi> did paſs to her, ſhe being not Heir to King <hi>Richard,</hi> but Succeſſor one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and all the Judges did reſolve that the <hi>Salvo</hi> did paſs to the Queen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Grotius,</hi> l. 2. c. 9. ſ. 8, 9. <hi>If a King dye without Iſſue in an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary Kingdom, the Empire remains in the Body of the People, who may create another, and limit him, the People being</hi> ſui Juris. Now in ſuch a caſe a Convention of the People duly aſſembled in their Repreſentatives, is the moſt Auguſt Aſſembly, even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond a <hi>Parliament,</hi> for to be able to make a King, is more than to be a King: and as the Original of Majeſty is fundamental<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the people, a <hi>Parliament</hi> hath a great dependance on the King, being his Subjects, the <hi>Convention</hi> is Abſolute and Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent, it makes bounds for the Monarch; and whereas one <hi>Parliament</hi> may repeal the Acts of another, a <hi>Parliament</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not alter the fundamental Conſtitutions of a <hi>Convention,</hi> when it firſt, conſtitutes a Monarchy. And this hath been the moſt ancient manner in caſes of great Neceſſity, the people aſſembled in a <hi>Folke mote,</hi> in the ſeveral Counties, and choſe their <hi>Wittena Gemote,</hi> or Meeting of Wiſemen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> The King was forced to leave his Kingdom, his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects failing to aſſiſt him againſt the Invaders.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:63211:32"/>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The queſtion that comes here to be conſidered i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Whether the Kings departure were voluntary or forced: It is certain that the actions of reaſonable men are generally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluenced by the propoſed end; for, <hi>Omnes beati eſſe volunt nec poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt velle contrarium,</hi> as all men deſire to be happy, ſo they cannot will any thing which they conceive to have a tendency to the contrary.</p>
               <p>Theſe two are generally the Originals of Humane actions, <hi>viz.</hi> Neceſſity and Choice; and Neceſſity is either that which we draw on ourſelves, or is impoſed on us by others. <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi>'s Oppreſſion of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was at firſt voluntary, while he hardned his heart againſt the Command of God, but when God gave him up to that hardneſs of heart, though the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of what he did became neceſſary, yet the principle that led him to it was voluntarily eſpouſed. 'Tis a Rule gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by <hi>Rainaudus,</hi> a good Caſuiſt, <hi>Modo preluceat notitia &amp; ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit coactio intervenit voluntarium:</hi> Where the underſtanding is ſatisfied concerning any deſign, and there be no force to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the proſecution of it, there our actions are voluntary. The end which the late King had long endeavoured, and with too much ſucceſs had by many means well nigh effected, was to make <hi>Popery</hi> the eſtabliſhed Religion of the Nation: He declared his deſire that all his Subjects were of the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion with himſelf; and his actions tended to make them ſuch: and doubtleſs he was not willing to have all his labours fruſtrated; when, therefore, he was reduced to ſome ſtraits, being ſuch as he wilfully brought on himſelf, he could not properly be ſaid to act by conſtraint. But this was not the King's caſe; that he did deliberate, whether to go or not, appears by his firſt departure and returning again, and then by departing ſtill under his own Guards a ſecond time, when he was by contrary Winds driven into <hi>Feverſham,</hi> he ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to quit the Land: So that if the late King had thought his carrying would have promoted his Intereſt, he would have ſtaid, but being guided by better hopes of compaſſing his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns abroad, it follows that he voluntarily, and I may ſay mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly deſerted us, deſtroying the Writs for calling a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, concealing the Broad-Seal, leaving us under the power of an Army of <hi>Iriſh Papiſts,</hi> whom he ordered to be Disband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without Pay; whereby he probably thought we would have crumbled into ſeveral Factions, and ſought it out among
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:63211:32"/>
ourſelves. All men count thoſe actions voluntary which were in their power to do or not to do, and though after delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the will be for a while in <hi>equilibrio,</hi> yet when other Reaſons and Circumſtances are added to make the Scales turn, the Reſolution and Actions that follow are our choice.</p>
               <p n="2">2dly, If it had been the preſent King's Deſign or Will to have hindred the late King's departure, he might have done it, and perhaps it might have been for his Intereſt to have ſo done; but by not doing it, he manifeſted that it was not his will to reſtrain him, but the late King's choice; for there was a Treaty offered and accepted by the late King, who ſent his Commiſſioners to treat with the Prince; but being (as by the event it appears) reſolved on his departure, he tarried not for the return of his Commiſſioners; and though he had appointed to meet his own Council in the Morning, yet he deſerted them in the Night before; to which, it is ſaid, he had engaged himſelf by Oath to the Queen. So that all theſe pretences of his being willing to remain in his Kingdom, were but to facilitate what he was more peremptorily reſolved to do <hi>(i. e.)</hi> to forſake it. So that tho' the conſequents of his own Actions, which were undoubtedly wilful, as his rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a ſtanding Army, which revolted from him, his abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Laws, ſubmitting the Kingdom to the Pope, and all thoſe Grievances ſumm'd up by the Lords and Commons, <hi>Feb.</hi> 12. brought a neceſſity on him to depart; yet ſeeing that neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity was the effect of his own Voluntary Actions, it muſt be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to his will and choice as the cauſe of it. And doubtleſs the King deſerted the Nation on ſome ſuch deliberations as theſe, He had followed ſuch evil and raſh Counſels, as had involved him in unextricable Troubles; his Counſellors were not able to defend him or themſelves, and by flight ſhifted for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. The Army, in which he confided, forſook him, the Affections of the People were generally alienated from him; ſo that the only Refuge that was left him was his truſty Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate the King of <hi>France,</hi> to whom he choſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit himſelf, rather than to ſubmit to a Treaty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But it may be Objected, That the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons were too haſty in declaring that the late King had Abdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated his Kingdoms, and that they ought to have treated with him, and propoſed ſuch Terms, as might have ſecured their Religion, Laws, and Liberties; to which if he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:63211:33"/>
all our Grievances might have been redreſſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this it is anſwered, That the Parliament, by their Votes againſt the Bill of Excluſion, had done as much as in them lay to engage him to a Faithful Execution of the Truſt repoſed in him <hi>(viz.)</hi> To Govern according to the Eſtabliſhed Laws. And his Promiſe to the Privy-Council im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately on his Brother's Death, did manifeſt what then was, or at leaſt ought to have been his Reſolution, for he declared, <hi>That he would make it his Endeavour to preſerve the Government both in Church and State as it was then eſtabliſhed. That he knew the Principles of the Church of</hi> England <hi>were for Monarchy, and that the Members of it had ſhewed themſelves good and Loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; therefore he would always take care to defend and ſupport it. I know</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>that the Laws of</hi> England <hi>are ſufficient to make the King as great a Monarch as I can wiſh; and as I ſhall never depart from the juſt Rights and Prerogatives of the Crown, ſo I ſhall never invade any man's Property. I have often adventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red my Life heretofore in Defence of this Nation, and I ſhall ſtill go as far as any Man in preſerving it in all its juſt Rights and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties.</hi> Theſe were Solemn Promiſes, to the performance whereof, not only his Honour, of which he boaſted, that he never had broken his Word with any Man, but his real In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt ſhould have obliged him; I cannot omit that Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Job, Chap.</hi> 34. <hi>ver.</hi> 30. <hi>That God in his righteous Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will not that an Hypocrite Reign, leſt the People be enſnared.</hi> Theſe were Divine Sentences in the King's Lips, but his Actions declared what was in his Heart, namely, to pull down and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all that he had promiſed to preſerve and defend with his very Life, to which the hope of ſalvation, being then a reſolved Papiſt, ſo pre-ingaged him, that in the perſwaſion wherein he then was, his conſcience muſt tell him he muſt periſh eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if he ſhould perform his promiſes, God only knows how to treat with ſuch Princes. It was not in the wiſdom or power of men to confine ſuch an Angel of light; for if by a Treaty the late King, under the circumſtances to which he was redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, ſhould have yielded to all the demands of his Subjects, his Allies abroad might, whenever they had an opportunity to aſſiſt him, have made all void, on pretence, that he was under force all the time of ſuch Treaty. And if he had been re-admitted with that freedom, honor and power which became a King of <hi>England,</hi> who could not foreſee, that as long as the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:63211:33"/>
Jeſuits had the guidance of his Conſcience, he would, a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time have renewed his Promiſes of eſtabliſhing our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Laws, and Liberties, only until he found another oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to deſtroy them, to which the Name of a King and his Preſence among his Subjects, and the Subtil Counſels and Deviliſh Arts of the Jeſuits, the Credulity of ſome, and the Diſcontents of many others, (for under the beſt Governments there will be Malecontents) would have made plauſible pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences and arguments for diſturbance of our peace, which our too powerful Neighbour, the King of <hi>France,</hi> hath for a long time, had incouragement from the late King to do, and only waited for an opportunity, and now declares he will endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to effect by open War. Thus <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Letter to Sir <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Throgmorton, Febr.</hi> 1. 1673/4. <hi>You well know, that when the Duke comes to be Maſter of our Affairs, the King of</hi> France <hi>will have reaſon to promiſe himſelf all things that he can deſire.</hi> And in another Letter to <hi>L' Cheeſe, that his Royal Highneſs was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, that his intereſt and the King of</hi> France<hi>'s were the ſame; and if his Royal Highneſs would endeavour to diſſolve the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the King of</hi> France <hi>would aſſist him with his Power and Purſe to have ſuch a new one as would be for their purpoſe, which was, the ſubduing of a peſtelent Hereſie that had domineer'd over a great part of the Northern World a long time, of which there were never ſuch hopes of ſucceſs ſince the death of Queen</hi> Mary, <hi>God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given us a Prince, who is become (I may ſay to a Miracle) zealous of being the Author and Inſtrument of ſo glorious a Work.</hi> See the <hi>Collection of Letters,</hi> p. 118. So that by what was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned by the Duke and <hi>French</hi> King, and hath ſince been jointly and vigorouſly acted, we have full aſſurance of a League with <hi>France</hi> for our utter ruin; and they are Fools or Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that having ſuch clear light and experience to guide them, will ſuffer themſelves to be blindfolded a ſecond time, and be led to deſtruction. So that what <hi>Joab</hi> ſaid to <hi>David</hi> is much more applicable in our Caſe; <hi>Thou lovedſt thine enemies and hatedſt thy friends, for thou haſt declared this day, that thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeſt neither the Prince nor his Servants, for this day I perceive that if the King had prevailed, and all they had died, then it had pleaſed thee well:</hi> So fond was <hi>David</hi> of his <hi>Abſolom,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.6.</p>
               <p>It is not neceſſary that abdication of an Office ſhould alway be an act of the will. <hi>Lentulus</hi> is ſaid to abdicate the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulſhip,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:63211:34"/>
becauſe he could hold it no longer, having been one of the Conſpirators with <hi>Gatiline;</hi> And <hi>Silla</hi> abdicated the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctatorſhip, thinking to find a better opportunity be to revenged on his enemies; And <hi>Diocleſian</hi> left the Empire becauſe he could not effect his will againſt the Chriſtians. Theſe were mixt actions, partly through conſtraint, and partly voluntary, yet were accounted abdications. And our King had involved us in ſo many miſeries, that nothing but his deſertion of us or our oppoſing of him could deliver us, God prevented the latter, and the King granted the former.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pufendorf de interregno,</hi> p. 272. determines, <hi>that if a King ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicates the peace of his Kingdom, and be of an hoſtile mind, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts from the Rules of governing,</hi> (which he expreſſeth thus, <hi>(Modum habendi poteſtatem immutare) that then the ground of the Subjects obedience is made void.</hi> And in the Digeſts, <hi>l.</hi> 49. <hi>Tital.</hi> 15. <hi>de Capt.</hi> we have this Maxim, <hi>Qui fuget ad eos cum quibus nulla est amicitia à fide ſuſcepta transfugit;</hi> and that the late King hath ſo done, is an evident truth.</p>
               <p>And it is as true, that to deſert a Government, rather than to keep it on juſt and legal terms, is to abdicate it; for an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication may be as expreſly ſignified by real deeds, as by any form of words whatſoever.</p>
               <p>As to the League with <hi>France,</hi> for making King <hi>James</hi> as Abſolute as King <hi>Lewis,</hi> and inable him (notwithſtanding his Oaths and Publick Declarations to the contrary) to extirpate the Proteſtant Religion, there wants not ſufficient evidence of the endeavours of the Court of <hi>France</hi> for many years together, by correſpondence with the late K. while he was Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and aſſum'd on him the chief adminiſtration of Publick Affairs: Nor of a too fond (if not a willing) compliance of <hi>Charles</hi> the Second to that end. Some wiſe men have thought that the great Revenues granted to the Crown, the declaring the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia to be wholly in the King, the binding up not only the Subjects but the Parliament by Oaths and Declarations not to reſiſt the King, or thoſe that were commiſſioned by him, on any pretence or cauſe whatſoever, by vertue whereof, an hundred <hi>Iriſh</hi> or <hi>French</hi> might have come into the Houſe of Parliament and out all their Throats, and they not have dared to draw a Sword in their own defence; all which things were againſt or as far beſides the Laws of the Land, as of Reaſon, and Common Prudence; for doubtleſs had it been propoſed
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:63211:34"/>
whether thoſe Laws might have been ſo interpreted, they would ſpeedily have made an alteration in them.</p>
               <p>All theſe I ſay have been obſerved by wiſe men, to have been the deſigns of ſuch as deſigned to introduce an Arbitrary Government, and facilitate the bringing in of Popery, though they that acted did not intend to ſerve the ends either of <hi>France</hi> or the Crown of <hi>England</hi> ſo far. On this Errand, was the Dutcheſs of <hi>Orleance</hi> ſome years ſince ſent into <hi>England,</hi> to aſſure <hi>Charles</hi> the Second of the Aſſiſtance of the King of <hi>France</hi> in reducing the Parliament to the King's pleaſure; to this end were Tolerations and Indulgences granted, <hi>French</hi> Whores ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, with great power and pomp, and all things ſo well prepared, though more ſlowly and ſecretly in the Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, that there wanted nothing but <hi>James</hi> the Second's aſcending the Throne to give a <hi>Conſummatum est</hi> to that deſign of bringing in both Popery and Slavery, upon us. And that being effected too ſoon alas for <hi>England,</hi> then not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Coronation-Oath, the many Publick Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations to maintain the Church of <hi>England</hi> and the Proteſtant Religion, and of whoſe Loyalty he was well ſatisfied, and that he never deſired to be more great and happy than he might be by the eſtabliſhed Laws; yet all theſe were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten and trampled under foot, Jeſuits and Papiſts being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted at Court, and into the Privy-Council, the King's Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſubmitted to their Conduct, the Pope's <hi>Nuncio</hi> publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entertained and feaſted at the <hi>Guild-hall,</hi> an Embaſſador ſent to <hi>Rome,</hi> Popiſh Biſhops ſet up with power of Juriſdiction, Proteſtant Biſhops put into the <hi>Tower,</hi> the Nobles cloſetted, and ſuch as would not comply to betray their Religion and Country, were turn'd out of all the chief Offices by Sea and Land, and others put into their room, and in all places of Judicature Judges and Juries were adapted for the proſecution of that deſign, there wanted only a complying Parliament; and to that end <hi>Quo Warranto's</hi> were iſſued out againſt the Charters, and alterations made in them fit for that deſign; Addreſſes were procured for taking off the <hi>Teſt</hi> and <hi>Penal Laws, (i. e.)</hi> for introducing of Popery by Law; an Army of <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts brought in, and another prepared in <hi>France.</hi> So that our deſtruction was much nearer than we believed.</p>
               <p>Monſieur <hi>D'Avaux,</hi> Embaſſador for the King of <hi>France</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> in his Memorial, told the Eſtates, that the Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:63211:35"/>
and Alliance between his Maſter and the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> did oblige him to aſſiſt the King of <hi>England,</hi> and to look on the firſt act of Hoſtility by Sea or Land, as a Rupture of Peace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Letters ſpake to the ſame effect, and the event hath demonſtrated the truth of all that was thought to be but groundleſs fears and jealouſies; for on the approach of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> theſe dark miſts vaniſh'd, the Nation awak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of their deep ſlumber, and reſum'd their ancient valour and reſolution to defend their Religion, Laws, and Liberties againſt Popery and Arbitrary Government, which ſeized on us as an armed man. And he that doth not now believe the <hi>French</hi> League, for introducing of Popery and Arbitrary Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, is worſe than an Infidel.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But the King forſook the Land becauſe his Subjects had firſt forſaken him contrary to their Duty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The peoples duty was to be governed according to the Law, which is the meaſure of their Obedience; and they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſenſible that the King's deſign was to ſubvert the Laws, and to that end had armed <hi>Iriſh</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Papiſts contrary to Law, they could not joyn with ſuch men in ſuch a deſign. The <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves alway oppoſed their Kings, in the reigns of King <hi>John, Henry</hi> the Third, and others, that would have ſubmitted the Kingdom to the <hi>Pope.</hi> And if the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects had fought for the King in this Cauſe, they had fought for the <hi>Pope,</hi> and for Slavery, againſt the Crown and Dignity of the King, againſt their Religion and Liberties, and againſt the Oaths of Supremacy and Allegiance, which bound them <hi>pro poſſe,</hi> as far as they were able, to reſiſt the Uſurpations of the <hi>Pope,</hi> by what means ſoever they ſhould be introduced.</p>
               <p>In brief, let this Dilemma be conſidered, either the King was forced to flye, or elſe he deſerted the Government willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; if he was forced, then there was a Conqueſt, and the Conqueror had right to what by lawful Arms he did obtain; if he fled willingly, then there was a renouncing of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that is an Abdication, and ſo the Crown became void, and our Allegiance to the late King ceaſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But the Subjects of <hi>England</hi> entred into an Aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the <hi>Prince,</hi> and though they fought not, yet were in Arms.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The <hi>Magna Charta</hi> granted by King <hi>John,</hi> (as well as
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:63211:35"/>
the Law of Nature) and confirmed by many Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, doth warrant ſuch an Aſſociation for preſerving their Lives, Laws, and Liberties, when they are in imminent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; and ſuch was the Caſe of <hi>England</hi> at that time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> If Subjects have Power to reſiſt their Princes, why then did the Primitive Martyrs caſt away their Lives, died <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> as a fool dieth?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> They had no Laws for eſtabliſhing their Religion, no Votes in chooſing the Senators, the Laws were againſt them, and their Religion obliged them to ſubmit to the preſent Powers who had an Abſolute Command over them; and if theſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians had ſuch Oaths from their Emperors as we have, it might be well queſtioned whether they would not have held him to the performance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> If we may not reſiſt a King, acting contrary to the Laws of God, and Nature, then neither when he acts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Laws of the Land.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Laws of the Land do grant to Subjects more particular Rights and Liberties than the Law of God doth, and the Law of God doth not deſtroy the Civil Conſtitutions of a Land, which the People may claim and defend; it is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore obſervable, that Queen <hi>Mary</hi> did not put any to Death for their Religion, untill ſhe had procured a Parliament that made void the Laws made on behalf of the Proteſtants, and had reinforced the ancient Laws which were made in times of Popery, and procured new ones againſt Proteſtants as He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks.</p>
               <p>It is a ſtrange account which Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtories gives of the Primitive Chriſtians, that they were <hi>Candidati Marty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> offered themſelves to their Perſecutors, not only when they were accuſed and brought before Magiſtrates, but when the <hi>Inimicum vulgus</hi> invaded them, and they might have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted ſuch as had no Authority againſt them; it was a Rule with <hi>Tertul. Quodcunque non licet in Imperatorem nec in quenquam licet:</hi> By which Rule it was as unlawful to reſiſt a Robber, or Murtherer, as the Emperor, and in his opinion, if the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror had been a Chriſtian, he might not have reſiſted any violent perſon, but he was a <hi>Montaniſt,</hi> and had his Errors, as in matters of Doctrine, ſo alſo of Fact, as in his Account that the number of Chriſtians were ſufficient to have van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed the whole Roman Empire, that it was not lawful to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:63211:36"/>
fly in times of Perſecution; to which end he wrote a Tract, <hi>De fuga,</hi> &amp;c. which was contrary to our Saviours direction to his Diſciples, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.23. And in truth, if it be not lawful to reſiſt a Perſecutor, neither is it lawful to fly when we are ſummoned to appear before a perſecuting Magiſtrate, for that is determined to be a kind of Reſiſtance: But the true Cauſe of the Non-reſiſtance of the Primitve Chriſtians, was that which <hi>Tertul.</hi> obſerves, <hi>Nos externi ſumus,</hi> We are Aliens from the Common-wealth of <hi>Rome;</hi> they had no Laws, no Votes in chooſing the Senators, but were accounted of as Out laws and Enemies to the Government, by their Religion; it was with them, as with ſuch Proteſtants as live under the Tyranny of the Pope, who being apprehended, and caſt into the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition, had neither Power nor Right to defend themſelves; but it was their duty to give Teſtimony to the Truth, by lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down their Lives for it. They were under an Arbitrary Power in the nature of Slaves, and Vaſſels, and lookt on as Enemies to the Roman State, being of a Religion contrary to what was eſtabliſhed; but we are Freemen, that have our Religion and Properties eſtabliſhed by Law, and ſuch as act contrary to the Government, reſiſt the Ordinance of God, and oppoſe it, and may be reſiſted. And the Oaths by which we are obliged bind us primarily to the Government, and to the Governours for the ſake thereof, and if the Government be not Arbitrary, neither is our Allegiance due to one that would govern Arbitrarily. So that ſuffering for the Faith of Chriſt, is a diſtinct thing from ſuffering for the frame of the Government; for if I may not reſiſt, I am overcome, and yield conſent to a change of the Government, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> to an Arbitrary and Illegal Power contrary to the Conſtitution un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der wich I live, and ſo promote the ends of an Oppreſſing and Uſurping Governour; and I cannot expect with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort a Reward from God, for caſting away my own Life, and endangering the Lives of many others, when a Government is duely eſtabliſhed, God approves of it as his Ordinance, and the People ought by all lawful means to preſerve it, for the Goſpel of Chriſt doth no more deſtroy the priviledges of the People than of the Prince, but if the Prince would deſtroy the Rights of the People, they may conteſt them; for in vain are Laws made, and Liberties granted, if they may not be defended.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:63211:36"/>And this may ſerve to anſwer the Objection concerning, the behaviour of the Primitive Chriſtians, who as Biſhop <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot</hi> obſerved, when they were armed with publick Laws, and Priviledges under <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> did not ſubmit, as when they lived under <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> and <hi>Licinius,</hi> but fought in their own Defence, and would rather kill than be killed. From the Death of <hi>Nero,</hi> the Chriſtians until <hi>Conſtantines</hi> Reign, thought it a great happineſs to injoy their Religion with Perſecution; they ſerved the preſent Emperours, fought their Battles, and took the Military Oaths, though the Emperor made way to the Throne by the Murther of his Predeceſſor, they diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not the Title, but did their preſent duty, as alſo did the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> under many Revolutions and Uſurpations of Government, when the younger hath been preferred to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed before the elder, and one Prince came in by the violent Death of another: And this was done in Succeſſion of the Prieſthood alſo, for whereas the High Prieſt was to be of the firſt born of <hi>Aaron,</hi> who left two Sons, <hi>Eleazar,</hi> and <hi>Ithamar,</hi> it is evident, that that Office was tranſlated from the Houſe of <hi>Eleazar</hi> the elder Brother, unto the Family of <hi>Ithamar</hi> the younger, and ſo continued for ſome Succeſſions, until it was return'd again to the Houſe of <hi>Eleazar,</hi> in the perſon of <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dok, Abiatha, vis abdicatione &amp; Zadoci ſubſtitutione,</hi> as <hi>Selden de Succeſſ.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 128. And as to <hi>Annas,</hi> and <hi>Caiphas</hi> mentioned in the Goſples, and the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles to whom Chriſt and the Apoſtle ſubmitted, as to the High Prieſt; it is evident, that <hi>Annas</hi> was thruſt in by <hi>Quirinius</hi> the Roman Preſident; as <hi>Selden,</hi> p. 174. and <hi>Caiphas</hi> thruſt himſelf in by the aſſiſtance of <hi>Gratus,</hi> to ſucceed <hi>Simon, (ibidem)</hi> and of them and ſome others of the High Prieſts; <hi>Selden</hi> obſerves from <hi>Joſephus, Singuli incedebant ſtipati manu audaciſſimorum &amp; ſeditioſorum hominum,</hi> p. 183. <hi>Edit. Londini,</hi> 1636.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 1. The Exception from a general Rule muſt be as evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent as the general Rule is. But the Exception, <hi>viz. King</hi> James <hi>is not the higer Power, is not as evident as the general Rule,</hi> viz. <hi>Let every Soul be Subject,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Exception is not good.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The major Propoſition I admit, if by (as Evident) you mean a Moral Evidence reſulting from the Nature and Properties of things? but if you mean that the Exception muſt be as expreſly, and diſtinctly ſet down, I deny it. <hi>Do no manner of Work,</hi> &amp;c. is a general Precept, yet caſes of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:63211:37"/>
were always excepted, though not particularly expreſt. So Children Obey your Parents in all things, as a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Precept,<note place="margin">Periculum vitae tollit Sabbat.</note> yet caſes <hi>Extra limites diſciplinae,</hi> are excepted. Jeſting is not once to be named among Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, as a general Rule, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.4. Yet Dr. <hi>Barrow</hi> ſhews many Exceptions which are not ſet down in Scripture. The like may be ſaid of that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Servants Obey your Maſters in all things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo the prohibition of eating Bloud admits Excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, though not mentioned in Scripture, for caſes of extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Nature, of Neceſſity, and rare Contingency, are not within the Intention of general Precepts, according to that known Maxim, <hi>De raro contingentibus leges non decernunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus though the Rule in Scripture he General, and Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation be the Penalty, yet on good Moral Evidence Excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may be admitted. Every one was not guilty of breaking the Sabbath that performed a work of Charity, or relieved his Neighbours Ox, or Aſs, or ſupplied his own Neceſſities on the Sabbath-day.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Minor may be reſolved into two parts. 1ſt, That the Precept, <hi>Let every Soul,</hi> &amp;c. is a general Precept. 2dly, That King <hi>James</hi> is the Higher Power. To the firſt, The Precept is General as to the perſons commanded, but what degree of Subjection is due, and who are the Higher Powers, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles defines not. The Apoſtle ſays (every perſon) in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Jews and Heretical Chriſtians, who thought themſelves priviledg'd, being God's peculiar people from Subjection to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Governours, and he ſays not, that the Subjection is to be Abſolute, and unlimitted, (for if this were his meaning, then all Governments ſhould be alike Abſolute) ſo that the Minor ſhould be thus expreſt, <hi>Let every perſon be ſubject to the Higher Power in ſuch a degree of Subjection, as the particular Conſtitution of each Nation requireth;</hi> in which ſenſe it will not ſerve the Hypotheſis. And certain it is, the Goſpel doth not diſannul any legal Conſtitutions agreed on between Prince and People.</p>
               <p>The 2d. part of your Minor is, That King <hi>James</hi> is the Higher Power.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> firſt, King <hi>James</hi> is not now the Higher Power. A Title without Poſſeſſion cannot be the Higher Power in this Text, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. or indeed in any other place. The power here mentioned is a power that hath the Sword, ſo that thô his Title were good, yet being out of Poſſeſſion, he is not
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:63211:37"/>
capable of having this Subjection paid to him; he hath not now the power of the Sword to puniſh Evil-doers, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Good, which is the end of Government.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Agreeable hereunto, a bare Title to the Crown, when another is in Poſſeſſion, doth not make our <hi>Seignior L'Roy</hi> in the Eye of the Law, in which point our Law Books are clear, which Books being never Cenſured, but Liſenced, (although the Government hath at all times been careful to cenſure and expunge ſuch Tenets as might prove dangerous to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, as was ordered to be done by the Lord <hi>Cook</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports in King <hi>James</hi>'s Reign) are thereby approved by the Government.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If a juſt War may extinguiſh a Right, then King <hi>James</hi> his Right is extinguiſhed, but a juſt War may, <hi>&amp;c. Ergo,</hi> The Minor is apparent as all political Writers, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Inſtances in Scripture do aſſert. The Sequel is clear, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe nothing is wanting to make this War againſt King <hi>James</hi> lawful, and capable to extinguiſh a Right: The War was juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly undertaken by the preſent King, and King <hi>James</hi> ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to his Arms is apparent, which is enough to extinguiſh his Right, had he made no other Forfeiture thereof.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Seeing the Apoſtle mentioneth the power in the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract, he ſeems to intend the Government, and the perſon that was Governour <hi>de Facto;</hi> for as <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> on the place, <hi>Non anxie diſputandum quo jure quare injuria Principes adepti ſunt ſuam poteſtatem, illud potius agendum eſt ut Magiſtratus preſentes revereamur.</hi> And as Biſhop <hi>Morton</hi> ſays, <hi>As ſoon as Princes are eſtabliſhed, whatever they be they may not be eſtabliſhed, for as ſoon as it becomes</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>it is</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>God's Ordinance.</hi> And if <hi>Nero</hi> were indeed the Emperor <hi>De Jure,</hi> the Senate ſhewed how little ſubjection they owed him, when as ſoon as he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew himſelf, they adjudged him an Enemy to the Common-wealth, and ſentenced him to die more <hi>Majorum, (i.e.)</hi> to be faſtned to the Earth Naked, by a Fork on his Neck, and to be beaten to Death with Rods, as <hi>Suetonius</hi> relates, <hi>in vita Neronis, S.</hi> 49. and therefore the Apoſtle ſeems not to intend the perſon of <hi>Nero,</hi> but the <hi>Roman</hi> Government, not deciding whether it were in <hi>Nero,</hi> or the Senate.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There is another Exception to the Second part of the Minor, <hi>viz.</hi> King <hi>James</hi> was never the higher Power, ſo as to have it ſolely in himſelf, ſome part of it was in the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:63211:38"/>
which had a Negative in the Legiſlation; and as to the Executive part, the Judgment of matters of Fact was in the People, <hi>viz.</hi> in Jurors, and the Election of Sheriffs, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently the diſpoſing of the Militia, and many great Offices both by Sea and Land, and the Judicial part was left to the King, confined by certain Methods, the King in Perſon not being able to decide the leaſt Cauſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. I thus except againſt the Minor. The ſubjection re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in the Text is due to the King's Perſon, for the ſake of the Power, and therefore is not to be extended farther than the Power wherewith he is inveſted, and with a <hi>Salvo</hi> to that part of the Power which is veſted in another; ſo that we owed no ſuch ſubjection to King <hi>James</hi> as did derogate from anothers Right, beyond the extent of his own Power, which was not abſolute, but limited by Law.</p>
               <p>And let this be conſidered from the Objection.</p>
               <p>Thoſe actions which will produce miſcheivous conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſhould not be ingaged in without moſt clear evidence of being our duty.</p>
               <p>But to refuſe Submiſſion to the preſent Government, will produce, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> therefore they are not to be ingaged in without moſt clear evidence, which, as things now ſtand, cannot be accounted clear and undubetable in relation to King <hi>James.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 2. <hi>The King can do no wrong;</hi> and therefore is not to be dealt with as a Malefactor.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> As to your Maxim, <hi>The King can do no wrong,</hi> if it be underſtood of the King's private or perſonal capacity, it may be thus retorted: <hi>The King can do no wrong;</hi> but he that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth, raviſheth, or murders an innocent perſon, doth wrong, therefore he is not King, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> in ſuch actions he is not to be conſidered as a King. But this Maxim, as many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, is to be underſtood of the King's political capacity, in which reſpect the Law is his Will, and the execution of the Laws are his Actions; in which ſence he can neither do wrong, nor ſuffer wrong, nor ever dyes. The true ſence of the Maxim is this, as Sir <hi>Edw. Cooke, Id poteſt quod jure poteſt;</hi> and this he ſays is the King's greateſt priviledge, which makes him like unto God, who cannot act but agreeably to the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Rules of Juſtice; but the King acting by his own Will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Law, may do wrong; and Judgment hath been given againſt him for unjuſt and illegal Actions. And doubtleſs
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:63211:38"/>
King <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, that would have ſubjected the Kingdom to the Pope, (as King <hi>James</hi> alſo would) cannot be exempted from doing wrong, though, as it was neceſſary, he muſt uſe many Inſtruments therein. <hi>Ahab</hi> did wrong <hi>Naboth</hi> in taking away his Vineyard, as well as his Inſtruments that did act under colour of Law.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 3. That King that is not accountable to his people for any wrong done, is not by them Coercible into a private eſtate; but the King of <hi>England</hi> is not accountable, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is not Coercible.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Argument is beſides the Buſineſs; for the People of <hi>England</hi> do not Coerce the King to a private Eſtate; but if he attempt to alter the Government and Religion, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave and deſtroy the People, they may uſe the remedy which the Law of Nature allows. <hi>Moderamen inculpatae tutelae:</hi> The Law not having appointed a legal remedy againſt the unjuſt oppreſſions of Princes, doth not render it ſinful to uſe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies allowed by the Law of Nature: for the Laws grew up gradually, and legal remedies were introduc'd occaſional<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, before the inſtitution of which remedies, it was not ſinful to uſe extraordinary remedies, as to kill <hi>ſe defendendo,</hi> to pull down Houſes in caſe of Fire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2. The Law provides remedies for caſes within its own compaſs, but not for caſes that may happen when the Law itſelf ſhall be ſubverted; it is unreaſonable to expect from written Laws any directions how Subjects muſt behave themſelves, when the authority of the Laws ceaſeth.</p>
               <p>If our Laws have not provided for the caſes of the King's Lunacy, Extinction of the Royal Line, wilful Deſertion, doubtfulneſs of Title, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but leave us to the general Rules of Prudence and Diſcretion, the ſame may be affirmed in the preſent caſe. 3. What is not prohibited is lawful; the caſes of extraordinary nature are not included in general Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, according to that Maxim, <hi>Conſenſus in rebus magni pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicii ex verbiis quantumvis generalibus non preſumitur:</hi> And <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſione generali nemo preſumitur ea conceſſiſſe quae in ſpecie vere ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter non eſſet conceſſurus.</hi> And it cannot be preſum'd that the Law would conſent that the King might at his pleaſure de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy their Lives as well as their Laws, conſidering how tender the Laws have been to preſerve the Lives and Liberties of the Subjects, who have been always accounted a free People.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:63211:39"/>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 4. If the whole Executive Power of the Law is in the King, then all Laws to Coerce the King, are in effect null, becauſe Execution is the life of the Law: But the whole Executive Power, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the minor it is already ſhewn, in what caſes and reſpects the Executive Power of the Law is in the People; and in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſes the King cannot ſuſpend the Execution of the Laws by his perſonal Command, the Officers being bound by their Oaths as well as Law, to the due Execution of them. So that if the King in perſon ſhould make unlawful Entries, hinder the Execution of Writs and Judgments, break the Peace, head a Riot, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Sheriffs and other Officers are bound to ſuppreſs and oppoſe ſuch by their Oaths. If it be objected, that the caſe of the King's preſence makes an exception: I anſwer, Neither the Oaths nor the Laws makes any ſuch exception; And <hi>ubi Lex non diſtinguit non eſt diſtinguendum.</hi> Again, the Defence made againſt the King's illegal Aſſaults, is not an act of the Executive Power which is in the King, but of Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Right, for in caſes where the Law hath not provided a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, and particularly and expreſly prohibited Self-preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there we may recur to natural and moral Remedies, and every man is allowed to be his own Judge in caſe of imminent danger, when there is no time allowed, nor any Judge to be appealed to.</p>
               <p>You ſay, that if the King will pervert the great end for which he was appointed, and pervert the Laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then as <hi>Bracton</hi> ſays, <hi>Datur petitioni locus licet ei fraenum ponere; (i. e.)</hi> as you expound it, to curb him by Petitions, with holding Taxes, and queſtioning his Miniſters; there is no <hi>enſe recidendum</hi> in our Law.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To curb by Petition, is to bind with Ropes of Sand; to queſtion Miniſters, if the Executive Power be in the King, is to no purpoſe; and ſo to with-hold Taxes, if the King in the head of an Army, may compel them, nor yet is there any need of depoſing or cutting off, for <hi>Henry</hi> 3. was not ſo dealt with. If a King mix himſelf with Outlaws and Cut-throats (againſt which we may, and in ſome caſes are bound to riſe) and expoſe himſelf to Caſualties, the people cannot prevent that; the fault is his own. The Murder of <hi>Edw.</hi> 2. and <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. was done by private Aſſaſſines, diſown'd by Parliament, and puniſhed, or if that Age exceeded the limits of Self-defence,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:63211:39"/>
it will not prejudice ſuch as defend themſelves with modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And in vain are Rights granted and purchaſed, if they may not by any means be defended. As to the inſtance of Marriage; the Indiſſolubility of that no way infers the Indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolubility of the relation between King and people: for, firſt, Marriage itſelf in ſome caſes admits a Divorce, as in caſe of Adultery, (Impotency <hi>a vinculo,</hi>) and in caſes of Cruelty, <hi>a menſa &amp; toro;</hi> and in caſe of Deſertion, after certain time, the Law allows another Marriage.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Indiſſolubility of Marriage ſprings not from its being a Contract, but from a poſitive Law of God ſuper-ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: So that unleſs you can ſhew the like poſitive Precept for the Indiſſolubility of the relation between King and people, the argument holds not. 3. There ariſeth another diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence from the nature of the thing: a Nation cannot want a preſent Governour; ſo that if the King will not attend the Government, there is an abſolute neceſſity of ſeeking another, which is not ſo in the caſe of Marriage; for a deſerted Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is not ſo ſuddenly deſtroyed, as a deſerted Kingdom will be.</p>
               <p>As to the Argument from our own and other Writers, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Non-reſiſtance,</hi> &amp;c. I anſwer, as formerly, That gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rules reach not the particular caſes, which could not be foreſeen or provided againſt. And,</p>
               <p n="2">2. It may be ſaid without offence, that good Divines are not alway good Lawyers, (and the Law is the meaſure of our Obedience,) as appears by the Authors of the <hi>Erudition,</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Bancroft,</hi> the former makes the King's <hi>Proclamations</hi> as binding as a Law; the later told King <hi>James,</hi> in the preſence of <hi>Cooke</hi> and other Lawyers, that the King might call any Cauſe and judge it perſonally in his Chamber.</p>
               <p>And there have been as eminent men in the Church of a contrary opinion; Biſhop <hi>Jewel, Bilſon, Abbot,</hi> and the Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s reign, who contributed to the War which ſhe undertook in behalf of the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> which have been often quoted in the preſent Caſe, and do all approve of a Defenſive War in caſe of imminent Danger and Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, contrary to the eſtabliſhed Laws.</p>
               <p>As to Dr. <hi>Sanderſon</hi>'s Judgment, approved by the Univerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> That the Right of Subjection ſprings from the Right of Protection, and the King's neglect of his Office, doth not
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:63211:40"/>
free the Peoples Conſciences from the Bonds of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. That beſides the Right of Protection, an actual Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Government is abſolutely neceſſary, to prevent Confuſion and Anarchy.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A neglect to perform Duty amounts not to the caſe in hand, <hi>(viz.)</hi> viſible Attempts to ruine and deſtroy the people which he ſhould preſerve, wherein the King doth not abuſe his power, but acts beyond and without his lawful power.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The people defending themſelves in caſes of extream ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, differs from the diſcharging of them from their Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, (which the Doctor urgeth) yet the diſcharge of them from their Allegiance may follow, if the King will leave them to a ſtate of Nature and Confuſion, or ſubject them to ſuch Enemies as ſeek to deſtroy them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 5. <hi>The King never dyes;</hi> therefore when the Right paſſeth from the King, it was immediately to be devolved on the <hi>Princeſs of Orange.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. The deſcent of the Crown is limitable by the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Authority of the Kingdom, as appears firſt by practice, frequently in King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th's days, and in the Marriage of Q. <hi>Mary</hi> with King <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> and in the crowning of <hi>Henry</hi> the 7th.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It conſiſts with reaſon, the Right of Succeſſion being but a Humane Conſtitution, is alterable by a Humane Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution. If the Order of Succeſſion had been a Divine Right, it muſt have been ſo in all Nations, and unalterable; <hi>Nil magis naturale quam quo modo aliquid conſtituitur eodem diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluitur.</hi> And it appears, 3. By the Act of Parliament 13 <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz.</hi> and whereas the Recognition of King <hi>James</hi> is pleaded as a bar to that Act. <hi>Anſ.</hi> Doth the Recognition ſay, that henceforth the Succeſſion ſhould be as the Laws of <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> unalterable? No, they had another intent, <hi>viz.</hi> To ſilence the Diſputes that had been concerning King <hi>James</hi> his Title, upon a Statute enabling <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th to ſettle the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, which Settlement, for not obſerving the forms pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by that Statute, became void; and ſo there was ſome cauſe for making the Recognition.</p>
               <p>And whereas it's ſaid, that the Act 13 <hi>Eliz.</hi> was made to ſerve a preſent turn, <hi>(viz.)</hi> to ſecure Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> againſt the pretences of the Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi> it is clear, that it reſpects the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:63211:40"/>
future Succeſſion by making the penalty of a <hi>Praemunire</hi> the Sanction of that Law for future Ages.</p>
               <p>As for the Maxim, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That a contrary declaration of the will of the Lawgiver, doth abrogate the former. <hi>Anſ.</hi> Where is the Contrariety? The recognizing K. <hi>James</hi> his Title, which had fallen under diſputes, is not contrary to that Act; and beſides, it is averred, that an Act of Parliament cannot be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed but by expreſs mention of it; and as for the omiſſion of it in the late Statute-Books (for it ſtill ſtands in the ancient Books) this was rather done to ſerve a turn, than the Act of Q. <hi>Elizabeth, Anno</hi> 13, as is pretended.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly, The preſent Settlement is made by the Supreme Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Nation; for there is the conſent of the right Heir, and the People fully repreſented, which are eſſentially the Supreme Authority; the calling by Writs being only a formality, and forms ceaſe in caſes of neceſſity, becauſe forms were introduc'd for common caſes, to obviate frauds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But in caſes of neceſſity, and where no fraud is uſed, the forms are not neceſſary. 2. In caſes of doubtful Succeſſion, the extinction of the Royal Line, or Lunacy, or as the caſe of reſtoring K. <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, it is impoſſible to uſe all the Solemnities, and yet a juſt Settlement may be made without them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 6. The next Doubt is concerning the New Oath, whether it be aſſertory, or only promiſſory.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, it is apparent that this New Oath leaves out the aſſertory part in the Oath of Supremacy, and the alteration in ſo conſiderable a part, implies an alteration in the matter of the Oath as to that particular.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly, The Law doth not bind the Vulgar to inquire into the Titles of Kings; nor indeed are they capable to judge of Titles (for we muſt ſwear in Judgment); and if it be object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the Law binds us to aſſert the rightfulneſs of the King's Title in the Oath of Supremacy, that was only in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the Pope's pretences and uſurpations, which are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly apparent; therefore we have no reaſon to preſume that the Legiſlators intended to bind us by this New Oath to aſſert the legality of the Title of the Governour.</p>
               <p>The ancient Oaths of Homage and Fealty, required of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Lord from his Tenants, hath the ſame expreſſions as the preſent Oath: yet this Oath was not intended to aſſert the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:63211:41"/>
Lord's Title, in point of right, nor did it oblige the Tenant in caſe the Lord ſhould forfeit, alienate, or be diſſeiz'd.</p>
               <p n="4">4. An actual Obedience is ſufficient to ſecure the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and therefore we cannot preſume that it requires more; it doth not look backward to what is paſt, but reſpect only the future time.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If theſe reaſons make not the caſe clear, yet they ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it doubtful, and then this Maxim takes place, <hi>Contra eum qui a pertius potuit loqui facienda interpretatio.</hi> But of this more hath been ſaid in Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi>'s Reſolution of the Caſe of the Ingagement; againſt which if it be objected, That there is more included in the word Allegiance, than in thoſe of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing true and faithful. I anſwer, There ſeems to be leſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by that word, for Allegiance ſignifies Obedience ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Law; and not in illegal caſes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in which there is no Obedience due, becauſe there is no authority to require it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Lawfulneſs of Self-Defence.</head>
               <p n="1">1. If the <hi>Engliſh</hi> people are ſo far at the Prince's diſpoſal, as to have no right to defend their Lives againſt his illegal Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults, then they are in the ſtate of Slaves and Captives; but we are not in ſuch a ſtate, but Freemen and Proprietors, as the <hi>Magna Charta</hi> and the <hi>Petition of Right</hi> do evidence.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If to preſerve our lives, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> we may not uſe a defence, then we prefer the means before the end; but this is abſurd, therefore the firſt is ſo. And if any Government do deprive us of that priviledge which Nature grants us, it were better to have continued in a ſtate of Nature and Anarchy, then to come under ſuch a Government.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Laws cannot be ſo interpreted as to be illuſory, but to bound the King's power, and to give the people Rights; and yet to ſuffer him to deſtroy all at his pleaſure, is a meer illuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Laws.</p>
               <p n="4">4. What hath been publickly done, and never been cenſur'd in the moſt ſetled times, may be preſumed lawful, but the Defence of the Peoples Rights (as in the Barons Wars) was never publickly cenſured, but the matters contended for, were confirmed by ſeveral Charters, ratified by dreadful Imprecati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and vindicated by the expence of the Lives of the Nobles and People, therefore it may be preſumed to be lawful.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:63211:41"/>5. What is permitted by the Law of God and Nature, and is not forbidden by the Law of the Land, is lawful; but Self-defence is permitted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and is not forbidden by the Law of the Land, therefore it is lawful.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> The Declaration, that ſays, <hi>It is not lawful on any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence whatſoever, to take up Arms,</hi> &amp;c. forbids it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> General Prohibitions muſt not be extended to ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Caſes, as would have been expreſly excepted, if they had been expreſly propoſed: And they who united into Government, and made Laws to preſerve their Lives, would never have conſented to give one man power to cut all their Throats.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Treaſon includes Felony, and Felony Malice propenſe, but ſelf-defence implies no propenſe Malice; therefore it is neither Fellony nor Treaſon.</p>
               <p>Conſider theſe Maxims, <hi>Quod quiſque obtutelam corporis ſui fecerit jure feciſſe videtur quando copiam ſibi Judicis qui jus reddat non habet vim vi repellere omnia jura permittunt, a jure civile ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probatur modenamen inculpatae tutelae:</hi> So <hi>Grotius, Si corpus impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatur vi preſente cum periculo vitae non aliter vitabili, tunc bellum eſt licitum etiam cum interfectionem periculum inferentis (ratio) Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura quemque ſibi commendat &amp; jus eſt cuilibet ſe defendendi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra immanem ſaecutiam:</hi> So <hi>Barcl.</hi> cont. Monarchom. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>Non ſunt expectanda verbera ſed vel terrorem armorum ſufficere vel minas.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the King's Abrenunciation.</head>
               <p n="1">1. To deſtroy the Government, is, to renounce and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim it, for <hi>Animus perdendi &amp; retinendi non conſiſtunt. Nolle habere</hi> is the ſame with <hi>Renunciare,</hi> but King <hi>James</hi> attempted to deſtroy the Government, for to deſtroy the Eſſence and Form of a Government, and alter its ſpecies, is to deſtroy it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If the defence be lawful in the People, and [the Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the Prince, then the loſs of the Crown, or Right to govern doth legally follow. But the Defence and Invaſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> therefore the loſs of the Crown, and Right of Goverment is ceaſed, and conſequently ſo is our Allegiance.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To forſake a Kingdom, and leave it in a ſtate of Nature, is to diſclaim it; but the late King did ſo; therefore he diſclaimed it. The Major is clear, becauſe Government is neceſſary by an Antecedent Neceſſity to a particular Perſon's being made
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:63211:42"/>
a Governour; and therefore rather than to continue a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banded Multitude, a particular Man's Right or Title muſt ceaſe. The Minor is clear, becauſe he ſuſpended the Laws, ſtopt their courſe, carrying away the Broad Seal, diſcharging the Judges, and then withdrew, leaving us in confuſion. If it be objected, that he was forced to withdraw. <hi>Anſw.</hi> It was what by many voluntary Acts he had drawn on himſelf, and the laſt Act partakes of the Nature of thoſe Actions from whence it flowed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> It will be a very great Scandal to the Nation, and Church of <hi>England,</hi> to diſclaim their lawful King without Treating with him, and ſeeking Reconciliation upon redreſs of their Grievances.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Clergy and Nobles did often Treat by way of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, and humble Advice, but were rejected with Contempt. The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> began to Treat with the late King's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, who were returning with an Anſwer, but the King left the City the day before, and ever ſince hath put himſelf out of a Condition to Treat; having given up himſelf to the Conduct of ſuch as are Irreconcileable Enemies to our Nation, and Religion. None were more fit to Treat with the King than a free Parliament, which as the King had made impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible by his Method; ſo if it had been duly called, and cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, yet a force would have been pretended while the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> had any Army in the Nation. And what if the King had complied as <hi>Chriſtiern</hi> the Second, King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> who after his deſertion was received again, upon renewing his Oath, and ſubſcribing to Conditions, who not only brake them all, but inviting the Nobles and their Children to a Feaſt, cauſed them all to be ſlain. The King of <hi>France</hi> ſhews what Faith may given to the ſolemn and repeated Acts of Ambitious Princes, and the obſervance of the Coronation Oaths, and many publick Declarations by our King.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As to the caſe of Scandal, I know not any ſort of Chriſtians that can juſtly be ſcandalized at ſuch proceedings, or condemn that practice in others, which they allow in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. As for the Papiſts, the principles of their Religion oblige them not to endure a Prince of a different perſwaſion, who to their Power, and beyond it have endeavoured to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe any Prince whom they judge Heretical; the not owning of the Pope's Supremacy, is thought a ſufficient cauſe for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicating
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:63211:42"/>
firſt, and then depoſing ſuch a Prince, and incouraging the People to withdraw their Allegiance, and take Arms againſt them; witneſs the Bull of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> againſt Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> and the approbation of that helliſh Powder Plot againſt King <hi>James,</hi> for the contrivance whereof <hi>Garnet</hi> was numbred among their Saints at <hi>Rome;</hi> and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of Kings and Emperors of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Communion hath been often practiſed by the Pope in <hi>Germany, France,</hi> and other Countries, on fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous pretences, as the Hiſtory of former and later times doth abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly manifeſt. And our own Chronicles ſhew what was practiſed by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, when it was wholly at the devotion of the Pope, in depoſing one King, and chooſing another. And God forbid that any Proteſtant Nation ſhould be guilty of ſuch Principles, or Practices, as have been received and allowed of by the <hi>Romaniſts.</hi> Our caſe is vaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly different, as is evident by the Declaration of the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; the many Grievances therein mentioned, and the occaſion of a juſt War given to the preſent King, reduced the late King, who had wholly deſtroyed the Foundation and Species of the Government, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert the Nation, and to fly to <hi>France</hi> for refuge, leaving his People in Confuſion, and made it neceſſary for them to do what they have done, to prevent their utter deſtruction by thoſe Flames, which he having kindled, fled from them for his own ſecurity.</p>
               <p>Nor can any Proteſtant Nation be ſcandalized at our Tranſactions, they having done the ſame thing on a like occaſion. Thus the <hi>Swedes</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded <hi>Sigiſmond</hi> the Third, and his Heirs, for altering the eſtabliſhed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, by introducing Popery, and ſending his Son to be educated a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt; for violating his Oath, altering the Laws, raiſing Souldiers, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acting Money contrary to Law; cauſing a Nobleman to be aſſaſſinated for diſwading him from his illegal Practices, puniſhing ſuch as would not receive the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion, and deſerting his Country without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of his People, for which cauſes he was adjudged to have Abdicated his Kingdom, and the Nation choſe <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Sudermannia</hi> to ſucceed him. <hi>Chriſtiern</hi> the Second, King of <hi>Denmark</hi> was ſo dealt with by his People: and what the <hi>Hollanders</hi> did againſt the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and the <hi>Scot</hi> againſt Queen <hi>Mary</hi> is generally known; and neither of theſe can be ſcandalized at us, who have acted more innocently than the beſt of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> From the Act of 13 of Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> which makes it high Treaſon during her Reign, and forfeiture of Goods ever after, in any wiſe to hold or affirm that an Act of Parliament is not of ſufficient Force and Vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity to limit and bind the Crown of this Realm, and the deſcent limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and inheritance thereof. It is objected, that this Act concerns not the preſent caſe, ſeeing what is to be done for the deſcent and limitation of the Crown, is to be done by an Act of Parliament, but a Convention is no Parliament; and that Act was made only to ſerve the preſent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the Queen, againſt the Claims of the Queen of <hi>Scots.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:63211:43"/>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That in the circumſtances wherein we were left, there was this Remedy left us, and no other; the late King having immediately be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his departure deſtroyed the Writs for calling a Parliament, though he had prepared the Elections for ſuch a one as might ſerve his purpoſe. And an extraordinary Diſtemper requires unuſual Applications; yet this was the moſt uſual and proper means, for what could heal our Diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, but an unanimous agreement of the People, in chooſing a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, when a Parliament could not be had? And who were more able or likely to conſult for the common welfare, than the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and the Repreſentatives of the People duly Elected; with whom the King having left them in Perſon, left his Authority with them, and they became as Auguſt an Aſſembly, as ever any Senate of the Ancient <hi>Romans,</hi> when the Empire became void, who had the Power to create an Emperor; which alſo had been often practiſed by the Ancient <hi>Britains.</hi> Nor was it fit that the Nation ſhould continue without a King, leaſt every Man ſhould have <hi>done what ſeemed good in his own Eyes, as when there was no King in</hi> Iſrael. And though a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention have not the formality of a Parliament, yet that being not to be had, it hath a greater Power than a Parliament, becauſe they act not as Subjects, but a free People who may chooſe their King, and make ſuch Laws for Government, as ſhall not be in the Power of the King and Parliament to diſſolve, without the Diſſolution of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment itſelf, as when the Foundations are deſtroyed, the Fabrick muſt fall; nor was there any one to invalidate the Acts of a free Convention, as the King in Parliament might do by his Negative Voice.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And whereas it is objected, that the Act of 13 <hi>Eliz.</hi> reſpected on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Title of that Queen, and was made to ſerve the preſent turn; this is contrary to the expreſs Letter of the Act, which provides that ever after it ſhould be puniſhable with forfeiture of Goods in any wiſe, to hold or affirm that an Act of Parliament was not of ſufficient force, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So that this Act ſtill continues in force, as the reaſon of it doth, <hi>viz.</hi> to prevent the dangerous diſputes concerning the Succeſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But the Convention ought to have ſet the Crown on the right Heir, as the moſt likely means to prevent all Diſputes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw. Quod fieri non debuit factum valet,</hi> That which ought not to be done in more peaceable times, may be warrantably done in caſe of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent danger, and <hi>Neceſſitas cogit &amp; defendit.</hi> The Affairs of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were involved in ſo many Intricacies, by reaſon of a Confederacy of the Popiſh Princes againſt the Proteſtants throughout all <hi>Europe,</hi> and the delivering up of <hi>Ireland</hi> into the Poſſeſſion of the Papiſts, who alſo had the Command of the ſtrength of <hi>England</hi> by Sea and Land, that the Courage and Conduct of a Woman, though never ſo well qualified, could not be thought competent to wreſtle with ſo many and great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties; and who more fit to unite ſo Noble, but diſtorted a Member as the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> to the Body of the Proteſtants, than he who by mutual Conſent of the Princes of that perſwaſion, was choſen to be their
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:63211:43"/>
Head; who alſo being of the Bloud Royal, and having married the right Heir, was by her conſent, and by the conſent of the Princeſs <hi>Anne,</hi> as well as by the unanimous conſent of the Nation, choſen to ſtand as a Skreen between them and the Fury of the <hi>French</hi> King, to defend their Title to the Crown, which he had ſo ſucceſsfully recovered from a loſt condition; Or who ſo fit to wear the Crown, as he that won it for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and the Right Heirs, when otherwiſe they might have deſpaired of it? It was doubtleſs a commendable action of the Men of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to reſcue <hi>Jonathan</hi> from the Fury of his Father <hi>Saul,</hi> who ſought to deſtroy his life, as well as to defeat <hi>David</hi> of the Crown, to which God had appointed him to ſucceed: And it is as commendable in our Nation, to commit the defence of the Crown of <hi>England</hi> to that Heroick Perſon, who hath ſo wonderfully reſtored it to the right Line: And who can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend any Injury is done in that caſe, wherein all Parties that are concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, do expreſly agree and acquieſce?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But this was not agreeable to the Declaration of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> at his firſt coming to <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. The Prince declared, That he would refer all Matters in queſtion, to the Determination of a Parliament freely Elected; which doubtleſs he would have done, had the late King been as willing to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fide in the good will of his own People, as the Prince was, but having not Confidence to abide the Deciſion of a Parliament, he fruſtrated that end of the Prince.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 2. One end of the Prince's Invaſion was to vindicate the Title of his Lady, and that which he alſo had to the Crown; which being by the late King's raſhneſs and precipitation made void, it was neceſſarily devolved on the Convention to ſupply, and in the circumſtance wherein we were, they could not do otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> The <hi>Convention</hi> is no <hi>Parliament,</hi> and therefore can make no <hi>Laws,</hi> much leſs can it diſpoſe of the <hi>Crown.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Though the <hi>Convention</hi> want the formality of being called by the King's Writ, yet it hath the power and authority of a <hi>Parliament,</hi> and in ſome caſes greater, as hath been ſhewn, and may thus farther appear: In the 36 of <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, we have this Clauſe in the Statute, <hi>That for maintenance of theſe Acts,</hi> (viz. <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and others relating thereunto, for the Publick Good) <hi>and for the redreſs of Publick Greivan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which daily happen, a Parliament ſhall be holden every year;</hi> as was ordained by another Statute, <hi>viz.</hi> 4 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 14. Theſe Laws were never yet formally repealed; and the reaſon of a Law continuing, it is reaſon the Law ſhould be ſtill in force, eſpecially when it concerns our <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and other Statutes made to prevent the Miſchiefs and Grievances which daily happen. And Judge <hi>Vaghan</hi> in his Reports ſays, <hi>That in caſes which depend on fundamental Principles, millions of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents</hi> (to the contrary) <hi>are to no purpoſe.</hi> So that the neglect of obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſuch a fundamental Law as maintains our <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> cannot make thoſe Laws void.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:63211:44"/>In the Act for Triennial Parliaments, made in the Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, it was provided, <hi>That if the King ſhould fail to call a Parliament according to thoſe Statutes,</hi> (viz. 4 <hi>&amp;</hi> 36 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3.) <hi>The People ſhould meet without any Writs at all, and chooſe their Parliament-men.</hi> This Trien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial Act of <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt was repealed by another Act for Triennial Parliaments at the return of <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, becauſe it was thought that it intrenched on the King's Prerogative, to which, as the effect ſhews, they were too much devoted, wherein yet they took notice, <hi>That becauſe by ancient Statutes of the Realm, made in the Reign of</hi> Edw. <hi>the Third, Parliaments were to be held very often, it was enacted, That within three years after the determination of that preſent Parliament, Parliaments ſhould not be diſcontinued above three years at most, and ſhould be holden oftner if need required;</hi> but were omitted from <hi>October</hi> 1685, to the time that the Convention me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> above three years.</p>
               <p>Now if ever there was need for calling a Parliament, it was in the caſe of our late Revolution; and ſeeing the late King did then refuſe to call a Parliament, it was neceſſary that the People ſhould for the maintenance of our <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and other Statutes relating thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, otherwiſe we had been left without a remedy in our greateſt extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity; therefore I conclude, that the Convention had the power of a Parliament, and from thence, that by the Statute 13 <hi>Eliz.</hi> this preſent Parliament had the power of limiting the Deſcent of the Crown, which they have devolved on the preſent King and Queen, and that they are legally in the poſſeſſion of it, and all the Laws made by the preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, are obligatory to the Subjects.</p>
               <p>Concerning the Declaration, <hi>That it is not lawful on any pretence what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever to take Arms,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>What provocations the late great Indignities which both the Royal Family, and all Loyal Families had ſuffered in the late Rebellion, I need not ſay; and what oppoſition was made by ſome <hi>Parliament-men</hi> of both Houſes, at the paſſing of the Declaration, and by what ſecret and unſuſpected Arts and Inſinuations they were moved to paſs it; but certainly if the effects of it had been foreſeen, and they had conſidered maturely what ill concluſions might be inferred from thoſe premiſes, ſuch as the eſtabliſhing an Arbitrary Power, and ruling by a ſtanding Army, and deſtroying many wholſome and fundamental Laws, they would never have contributed to the eſtabliſhing of their own Slavery by a Law.</p>
               <p>Of this deſign the Parliament-men in both Houſes became ſenſible: And when in the thirteenth Seſſion of the Parliament, 1675, the like Declaration was required as a Teſt of all Parliament-men, in either Houſe, and of all Officers of Church and State, <hi>(viz.) I</hi> A. B. <hi>do declare, That it is not lawful on any pretence whatſoever, to take up Arms againſt the King,</hi> &amp;c. there was great oppoſition made againſt it, as a Bill of dangerous conſequence; inſomuch, as it was debated five ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral days in the Houſe of Lords, before it was committed to a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:63211:44"/>
of the whole Houſe.) The Lords that oppoſed it, were of great Quality for Paris and Intereſts; their Names, as I find them, were, <hi>Buckingham, Bridgewater, W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>cheſter, Salisbury, Bedford, Dorſet, Ali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bury, Briſtol, Dembigh, Pagist, Hollis, Peter, Howard</hi> of <hi>Berks, Mohun, Stamford, Hallifax, Delamore, E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re, Shaftsbury, Clarendon, Grey, Roll, Say and Seal, Wharton, Audley, Fitzwater.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Bill was intituled, <hi>An Act to prevent the Dangers which may ariſe from Perſons diſaffected to the Government.</hi> Divers amendments and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations were propoſed; ſome would have it run thus, in the ſecond part of it,—<hi>I do abhor that Traiterous Poſition of taking Arms by the King's Authority againſt his perſon, or againſt thoſe that are Commiſſioned by him, according to Law in time of Rebellion or War,</hi> &amp;c. And as to the third part, concerning Church-Government, ſome would have it run thus: <hi>I do ſwear not to endeavour by force or fraud to alter,</hi> &amp;c. Others thus: <hi>I do ſwear that I will not endeavour to alter the Proteſtant Religion now by Law eſtabliſhed in the Church of</hi> England. But the firſt part about taking up Arms, was moſt hotly diſputed: And firſt they debated the Form; whether there ſhould be any Oath in the Bill. Here they argued againſt the multiplying of Oaths; and that there was really no Security to any State by Oaths; and that no private Perſon, much leſs a Stateſman would ſo order his affairs, as to rely on them: No man would ever ſleep with open Doors, or unlockt Treaſure, or Plate, ſhould all the Town be ſworn not to rob. Then was the Aſſertory part of the Declaration debated, and it was urged, That Aſſertory Oaths and Declarations were proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appointed to give Teſtimony of a matter of Fact, of which a man may be aſſured by the evidence of his ſenſes, but not to confirm or inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidate Doctrinal Propoſitions; and that the Legiſlative Power which impoſeth ſuch an Oath, aſſumes to its ſelf an Infallibility, and muſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe all that take it to be infallible; which could not be ſuppoſed in ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and illiterate Men; and that Promiſſary Oaths in the judgment of <hi>Grotius, De Jure Belli,</hi> l. 2. c. 13. are forbidden by our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.34, 37. to be multiplied; and that to declare upon Oath, and to ſwear upon Oath, were the ſame thing: And that to declare up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Oath, <hi>That it was not lawful upon any pretence whatſoever, to take up Arms againſt the King,</hi> might introduce a new Form of Government; that it was better to leave ſuch things in Generals, as in the Law of 25 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. which makes it Treaſon to take up Arms againſt the King, and the reſtraint of it to any caſe whatſoever, would deſtroy the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction between Abſolute and Bounded Monarchies, if Monarchs have only the fear of God, and no fear of Man to reſtrain them; and that our Anceſtors took care that the Prince's ſafety ſhould be in them, and never would endure a mercenary or ſtanding Army, though Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioned by the King; and that the declaring an Abhorrance of that Traiterous Poſition of taking Arms by the King's Authority againſt his Perſon, being ſet down in univerſal Terms is not alway to be abhor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed as Traiterous, there being but one caſe, and ſuch as is not
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:63211:45"/>
like to happen again, wherein it was ſo, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> the Caſe of the Long Parliament; but other Caſes might and did often happen, wherein taking Arms againſt ſuch as were Commiſſioned by the King, might be the Subjects Duty; as in the inſtance of <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth, being taken Priſoner by <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth, who pretended to the Crown; and the Earl of <hi>Warwick</hi> who gave out what Commiſſions they plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; but his Wife and Son raiſed Arms againſt ſuch Commiſſions, and reſcued the King's perſon by fighting againſt ſuch Commiſſions; And laſtly, that not to take Arms againſt any that were Commiſſioned by the King, did evidently introduce Arbitrary Government; and if whatever is by the King's Commiſſion, is not to be oppoſed by the King's Authority, then a Standing Army is Law, whenever the King pleaſeth; and that the King's Commiſſion was never held ſufficient to juſtifie any Man acting againſt his Authority, which would deſtroy the moſt eſſential and fundamental part of Law for Liberty and Property, and make the Government Arbitrary. And it was urged, That if a Man recovers poſſeſſion of his Houſe, and is by the Sheriff put into it, and the perſon outed procure a Warrant to ſome Commiſſioned Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of a Standing Army, to deliver back<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Poſſeſſion, the perſon that is in poſſeſſion, by Law, may defend himſelf by Arms, againſt thoſe who by Commiſſion from the King come by force to Eject him out of his Poſſeſſion. So that ſuch a Declaration and Oath was to eſtabliſh another Government (which the Oath of Allegiance knew not,) and then ſwear to maintain it as eſtabliſhed. All this, and much more, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Declaration as it ſtands, after ſixteen or ſeventeen days ſpent in arguing, was confirmed, and the Conſequences plainly manifeſt, how unreaſonable it was in it ſelf, and how miſchievous to the Subjects; and therefore <hi>is by the Act</hi> 24 <hi>April last, laid aſide.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Preſent Oath.</head>
               <p>The Oath of Allegiance and Supremacy being abrogated, our Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance was reduced to the Oath of Allegiance, as it anciently ſtood, and was to be adminiſtred in the Court-Leet; the Form whereof runs thus: <hi>You ſhall ſwear that from this day forwards, you ſhall be true and faithful to our Soveraign Lord the King, his Heirs and lawful Succeſſors,</hi> &amp;c. which words do not aſſert the Title to the Crown, nor look backward to what is paſt, but aſſures Fidelity for the future; and our Legiſlators plainly declare, that by the words in the late Oath—<hi>I will be faithful and bear true Allegiance,</hi> is the ſame Fidelity meant, as in the Declaration ordered to be ſubſcribed by ſome Diſſenters, viz. <hi>To be true and faithful:</hi> And doubtleſs the Legiſlators who are of the ſame Communion in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> could not think of laying a greater reſtraint or obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation on the genuine Members of that Church, whom they have found to be always Faithful, then upon ſuch Diſſenters as had been falſe. And had the two Houſes thought or ſuſpected any ſnare in it, they would have
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:63211:45"/>
been ſo far from laying it on the Conſciences of others, that they would not have tought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> with one of their Fingers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So that our Legiſlators have in the Subſcription required from thoſe Diſſenters, clearly reſolved what they meant by the word <hi>Allegiance</hi> in the Oath, namely, <hi>To be true and faithful;</hi> in which ſence as many have declared they would take it, without any farther ſcruple: So I ſee no reaſon but all may, except ſuch unreaſonable Men, as bogling at ſhadows from the word <hi>Megiance,</hi> are reſolved to incur the ſad conſequences of being judged Rebellious.</p>
               <p>I have one Requeſt more, which I intreat ſuch of my Brethren as are yet Unreſolved, ſeriouſly to conſider, <hi>viz.</hi> That having devoted their Perſons and Services to Almighty God, in the Miniſtry of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> they cannot without the guilt of Sacriledge in a high degree, and upon very clear and demonſtrable Arguments, withdraw themſelves from that Miniſtry, eſpecially in ſuch a juncture of time; when there are ſo many grievous Wolves, ſome in Sheeps cloathing, and others with open mouths roaring for their Prey, that ſeek by all means to devour their Flocks; and by the loſs of her Miniſters, the Church itſelf may be in a ſhort time deſtroyed; for there are ſtill too many that bear evil will to <hi>Sion,</hi> and would down with it even to the ground: And if it ſhould be found, that we have forſaken the Service of God, on a Miſtake or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, when we ſhall be called to an account, how we have fulfilled our Miniſtry, and watched over the Flocks, whereof the Holy Ghoſt had made us Overſeers, we muſt have ſome ſubſtantial Reaſons to plead in our Excuſe, or we ſhall never render an Account with Joy. The Evil Spirit hath (not without a Miracle) been ſorely caſt out, and is roving up and down, ſeeking how to enter again; and if we by our Diviſions ſhould make a breach for him to enter by, <hi>he will bring with him ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold more, and dwell among us, and make our later end worſe than the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi> It is ſad when we ſhall be reduced to ſuch a condition as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time the <hi>Roman</hi> State was which could neither, <hi>ferre Vulnera nec Remedia,</hi> endure their Wounds nor the Remedies of them. If we by our Obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy do fruſtrate all the means of our Salvation, and receive the Grace of God in vain, and being fond of kiſſing the Rod that ſmote us, do reſiſt the Hand that would heal us, there muſt be a greater Miracle wrought for our Salvation, than hitherto God hath wrought for any man, that is, to ſave us againſt our wills: <hi>Cujus aures clauſae ſunt ut ab amico veritatem audire nolit, hujus Salus pene deſperanda est.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:63211:46"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>A Reſolution of Certain Queries, concerning Submiſſion to the Preſent Government.</p>
            <list>
               <head>The QUERIES.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>I.</hi> Concerning the Original of Government.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II.</hi> What is the Conſtitution of the Government of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>III.</hi> What Obligation lies on the King by the Coronati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on-Oath?</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> What Obligation lies on the Subject by the Oaths of Supremacy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>V.</hi> Whether if the King Violate his Oath, and actually Deſtroys the Ends of it, the Subjects are freed from their O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bligation to him?</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> Whether the King hath Renounced or Deſerted the Government?</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VII.</hi> Whether on ſuch Deſertion the People, to Preſerve themſelves from Confuſion, may admit Another, and what Method is to be uſed in ſuch Admiſſion?</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VIII.</hi> Whether the Settlement now made, is a Lawful E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhment, and ſuch as with a good Conſcience may be Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to?</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Divine of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>as by Law Eſtabliſh'd.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
